<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>BoldlyGoes</title>
    <description></description>
    <link>http://boldlygoes.com//</link>
    <atom:link href="http://boldlygoes.com//feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Thu, 17 Sep 2015 16:06:10 +0100</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 17 Sep 2015 16:06:10 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v2.5.3</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Exploring The Danube: A Plan Is Born</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Pest and Buda, once two separate cities, were connected permanently for the first time in 1849 by
the Chain Bridge, an impressive suspension
bridge spanning the 400 metre-wide River
Danube. Before its construction, crossing
between the two cities was a much more
arduous task, calling for the use of ferries
and improvised wooden bridges, and was
at all times entirely under the will of the
weather. In fact, the harsh Hungarian
winters could leave hopeful river-crossers
stranded for days or even weeks at a time.
That was until the river left Count István
Széchenyi, an ample-eyebrowed Hungarian
statesman, stuck and unable to cross the
river in order to attend his father’s funeral.
The unfortunate event inspired him to take action and commission the building of bridge large
enough to withstand anything the weather and the river’s power could throw at it. An English
engineer by the name of William Tierney Clark was handed the job of realising the Count’s vision.
He based the Chain Bridge on a small bridge he had built in Buckinghamshire crossing the
Thames in the village of Marlow. It was this bridge that first connected the two cities and served as
a catalyst in establishing the metropolis of Budapest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/f/fd/Sz%C3%A9chenyi_Chain_Bridge_in_Budapest_at_night.jpg&quot; data-lightbox=&quot;chainbridge-large&quot; data-title=&quot;The Chain Bridge spanning the Danube.&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/f/fd/Sz%C3%A9chenyi_Chain_Bridge_in_Budapest_at_night.jpg&quot; title=&quot;Check out the Falcon 9 from SpaceX&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we stood upon the Bridge under the beating sun and the
watchful eyes of two large limestone lions reminiscent of those in
Trafalgar square, we listened to our tour guide recite this story of
how the bridge had come to be. Around stood many like us, a
haggard group of Englishmen wearied by the previous night’s
consumption of alcohol and loud Euro-House. We were in beautiful
Budapest, nine-strong, celebrating the marriage of our friend
Alasdair. Whilst listening to our guide I couldn’t help but notice the
Danube beneath us. Wide and shimmering blue. All too inviting. I
pictured myself paddling down it on some future adventure and
casually suggested the idea to Raj and Harvey to which they casually concurred.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/assets/images/chain-bridge-lion.jpg&quot; data-lightbox=&quot;lion-large&quot; data-title=&quot;Check out the Falcon 9 from SpaceX&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/chain-bridge-lion.jpg&quot; title=&quot;One of four imposing limestone lions guarding the bridge.&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fast forward three weeks and the same group of Englishmen are well-oiled once again but this
time in an ornately decorated Hertfordshire village hall for Alasdair and Gabrielle’s wedding. The
passing thought of taking a trip down Europe’s second longest river had by now been stewing in 
my mind for some time. I had been secretly poring over maps of Europe, measuring the distances
between the River’s most notable sights and cities, reading up on canoes and packrafts. Silently
scheming. I had by this point already planned in my mind a journey between the once sprawling
Austro-Hungarian empire’s two capital cities: Vienna and Budapest. A journey of 250km passing
through Bratislava and Esztergom situated on the shoreline of the river’s main channel as well as a
maze of slowly shifting tributaries and offshoots in the vast floodplains of Dunajské luhy. I broached
the subject once more, this time a little less casually: “We should canoe down the Danube next
year, it’d be fun!”. Admittedly a little drunk we had perhaps unwisely begun our journey. Oh boy, we
have a lot to do!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 17 Sep 2015 16:19:22 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://boldlygoes.com//planning/2015/09/17/exploring-the-danube:-a-plan-is-born.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://boldlygoes.com//planning/2015/09/17/exploring-the-danube:-a-plan-is-born.html</guid>
        
        <category>budapest</category>
        
        <category>planning</category>
        
        <category>danube</category>
        
        <category>well-oiled</category>
        
        
        <category>planning</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
