<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Boldly Goes</title>
    <description>Three lads from Hertfordshire entertain you with articles on outdoor topics.</description>
    <link>/</link>
    <atom:link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Apr 2017 19:15:46 +0100</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 04 Apr 2017 19:15:46 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.1.6</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Scarpa Delta GTX Activ Review</title>
        <description>&lt;dl&gt;
  &lt;dt&gt;Pros&lt;/dt&gt;
  &lt;dd&gt;Quality materials and assembly&lt;/dd&gt;
  &lt;dd&gt;Reduced or non-existant wearing in period&lt;/dd&gt;
  &lt;dd&gt;Tough but responsive sole&lt;/dd&gt;
  &lt;dt&gt;Cons&lt;/dt&gt;
  &lt;dd&gt;Leather isn’t for everyone&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I bought these Scarpas in early spring 2016, for around £180 from GoOutdoors (from a physical shop for once!) and as far as I can see, they are the tough boots from the idiom. So far I’ve covered around 500 miles in them; wading through streams, walking over hills, climbing up mountains, stomping through snow, slogging through mud, and they have yet to let so much as a drop of water in. All the while they’ve provided a high level of comfort which I didn’t have to earn with a prolonged wearing in period, they fit comfortably right out of the shop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/deltagtx/first.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Drawn in by the leather look and instantly comfortable fit, my Deltas have only improved with age.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;quality&quot;&gt;Quality&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The majority of the boot is covered in a 2.4-2.6mm leather, with a calf’s leather upper and tongue joint.  Although a little stiff to begin with (as leather always is) creases wore in straight away at the ankle bend, providing that tailored fit that I have only ever experienced with leather boots.  They have picked up a few cosmetic bramble scratches over the last year, while these haven’t even come close to affecting the boots performance, they have left me a little self conscious about further damage in a way I probably wouldn’t feel wearing boots with a synthetic construction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The stitching, glue and general construction is all fantastic quality from what I have seen in the last 12 months, nothing has budged even a little bit.  The sole has hardly aged at all, its deep tread still as effective as day one, and even the inner sole is in good condition; still springy albeit missing some surface colour from wear.  The comfort level has only increased as I have worn them in, there have been no weak links when it comes to build and material quality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/deltagtx/quality.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;A year and several hundred miles in, all of the joints and stitches show no signs of shifting.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;design&quot;&gt;Design&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To compliment the great quality, Scarpa have realised a fantastic design to boot. They are a great mix of old and new boot style; comfortable, traditional calf and cow leather with hi-tech comfort inside and a Gore-tex waterproof lining, all topped off with a springy, bomb-proof, plastic sole. Having worn my pair in deep snow and at the height of summer without dampness creeping in and all sweat creeping out, I can say that the waterproofing and breathability of the Delta is fantastic.  The laces will stay put all day, even without a lace locking mechanism and although it’s quite tricky to get the tongue to stay in place to begin with, once you have worn them enough to mould the leather into place, lacing them up is a breeze.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sole is springy and manages to feel surprisingly responsive for what is quite a large chunk of plastic, even with the very sturdy toe protector at the front. I’ve felt thoroughly connected to the earth in them almost all the time, these boots are definitely built to make you feel like Godzilla crashing down a hill, rather than a highly tuned and nimble hill walker.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/deltagtx/design.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;The memory foam, insole and springy sole work harmoniously to provide a comfort level which hasn&#39;t faded.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The boots have what Scarpa calls “ActivFit”, which means Scarpa made the boot using a special ‘last’ which is the analogue for a human foot used to mould the inner padding. These hi-tech lasts apparently allow for a softer padding to be used inside the boot, and this abundance of soft cushioning is what makes the boots feel better than others right out of the box. The boots also feature a breathable memory foam innersole, which really doesn’t let you down when you find yourself standing for long periods of time eating lunch or waiting for others on the trail. Without knowing about any of these features at the time, I thought they felt better than all of the other boots I tried straight away and I have only had one incident with blisters, so apparently it all works.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;alternatives&quot;&gt;Alternatives&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The direct competitors in the 3 season leather boot range include the Mammut Brecon II, which costs ~£170 and the heavier Meindl Bhutan MFS, which costs ~£180.  Reading reviews of the competition, I am not instilled with confidence the way I was approaching Scarpa; build quality issues aren’t what you want to hear when investing in something you want to last up to 5 years.  There were actually several user reviews that included lines such as “&lt;a href=&quot;/media/img/deltagtx/scarpa-review.jpg&quot;&gt;never gonna last 10 years like my old Scarpas&lt;/a&gt;”, far reaching brand reputation for quality is always a good sign.  From what I have seen, the alternative with the most to offer comes from the British company Anatom, their Braeriach 3 season boot costs only £144 and has been reviewed positively so far.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/deltagtx/worn.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;final-thoughts&quot;&gt;Final thoughts&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With a regular oil and wax I can see these boots lasting me at least another 5 years,  if they remain this comfortable I’d be happy to wear them all that time too. Insulative, grippy, comfortable and visually pleasing; they tick all the right boxes and support you in all the right places.  I’ve recently seen them online as low as £160, so while not exactly a bargain, they are still very good value.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;rating-34&quot;&gt;Rating 3/4&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’d definitely reccomend them and would buy another pair in a heartbeat.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 04 Apr 2017 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>/reviews/delta-gtx-review</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/reviews/delta-gtx-review</guid>
        
        <category>reviews</category>
        
        
        <category>Reviews</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Going Ultralight: Repacking</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;In this series I’ll be taking you through my thought process as I shave the pounds off of my setup before I attempt some multiday hikes later this year.  I’ll be slimming my system down from a bloated giant which would drag me down with it, to a sleek ultralight bundle that I hardly notice as I skip along the cliffside like a mountain goat who’s just discovered weight watchers.  Hopefully you’ll find some tips that you can use with your gear, if you have any tips of your own, remember to share them in the comments!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Until now, the majority of my camping has involved setting up a base camp somewhere a few miles out from the car and day hiking to explore the surrounding area with only a day sack on my back.  Over the years this has led to quite a blasé attitude toward my gear purchases and how much I take with me, resulting in a very cluttered inventory of things I use rarely even though I carry them often.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/ultralight1/start.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Just a few of the things I have recently taken out with me, mostly useful but certainly not essential.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/ultralight1/stuff.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;The bits and bobs I&#39;ve aquired over the years always seem handy at the time but the weight adds up fast.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recently, however, I have planned a few more adventurous trips which will involve hiking and camping with everything on my back for two weeks or more, this is when lighter gear starts to seem very appealing.  Being outside is great fun; hiking, cycling, canoeing, camping, these have all been enjoyed as past times since the 1800s when camping and hiking were first popularised.  Things can be made much less fun, however, if you are forced to carry enormous weight while you partake in them, as was pointed out in one of my &lt;a href=&quot;/features/how-to-camp-out&quot;&gt;favourite books&lt;/a&gt;…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style=&quot;font-style: italic; font-weight: 800; font-size: 18px;&quot;&gt; &quot;Very few young men who read this book will find it possible to enjoy themselves, and carry more than twenty pounds a greater distance than ten miles a day, for a week.&quot; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-style: italic; font-weight: 400; font-size: 14px;&quot;&gt; - John M. Gould&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That was written in 1877.  Twenty pounds was more than the advised limit when hiking recreationally for an american civil war veteran.  He was surely a lot tougher than you or I, probably a fair bit stronger, and even he didn’t carry a heavy pack back when everything was made from either wool or iron.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These days a pack base weight of around 20lbs will class you as a ‘lightweight’ backpacker, but if it was too heavy in 1877, it’s certainly too heavy for my flimsy millennial bones today.  A pack weighing 5lbs will apparently see you classified as a ‘super-ultralight’ or ‘hyperlight’ backpacker.  From what I have seen, this weight is where you enter the realms of record breaking, astonishingly fast hikers who blaze past you with no time to concentrate on the scenery or get a trail name that doesn’t involve a superlative.  These hikernators usually forgo every creature comfort they can to save weight, and eat only food with the highest of calorie to weight ratios.  Because I’m not keen on re-hydrated beans, and wouldn’t mind the odd cup of coffee on the trail, I’m going to aim for the middle-ground. 10lbs. Ultralight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because I’m going to be making my trips in the summer (albeit a British summer) I’m going to presume a night temperature of around 10 Celsius and infrequent rain, so I’ll create my ultralight system with that in mind.  I’ll also aim for a system with a stove of some sort because I like warm meals at night and coffee in the morning but I am open to the idea of going stoveless, depending on my final weight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;repacking&quot;&gt;Repacking&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first step in lightening my pack is also the easiest and certainly the cheapest, I’m going to unpack everything and start from the beginning.  Starting from the bottom is going to force me to tackle everything I put into my pack; I’m looking at each item in a new light now, a revealing, minimalist, white light which isn’t flattering to anything but the essential.  I’m going to need to really think about how important everything is before I put it in my bag, and it’s likely my bag can lose some weight too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I repacked the first time, I picked up only the things which are directly linked to my survival outdoors; water, shelter and food.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/ultralight1/final.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;My essential gear.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is how my gear looks post repack:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;water&quot;&gt;Water&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Karrimor aluminium bottle 1.5L - 143g&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Lifeventure collapsible bottle - 52g&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Water purification tablets (x 30) - 10g&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Total - 205g&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;shelter--sleep-system&quot;&gt;Shelter (+ Sleep System)&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Alpkit Hunka - 390g&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Vango sleeping bag - 1621g&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Roll mat - 150g&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Total - 2161g&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;cooking&quot;&gt;Cooking&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Trangia Mini - 360g&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Meths container - 38g&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Spoon - 10g&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Total - 408g&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;total&quot;&gt;Total&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gear - 2774g&lt;br /&gt;
Regatta Survivor 65 pack - 1569g&lt;br /&gt;
Total pack base weight - &lt;strong&gt;4343g&lt;/strong&gt; - &lt;strong&gt;9lb 9.19oz&lt;/strong&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve already hit a decent starting point, and it’s only taken about 20 minutes.  Unless you’re cooking on a portable aga, at this point you should be pretty significantly below 15lbs, if not more, like me.  Here we have the essentials, as they were in my original pack, not particularly expensive or light but we’re already hovering around our goal weight.  Obviously there’s still a fair bit to add if I want to have a nice time while I hike: toiletries and perhaps some camp clothes, but we’ll get to that later in the series.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s actually quite a lot we can do to reduce the weight even at this point, that’s what I’ll be doing in part two of this series: Refining the essential - look out for that in April!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 30 Mar 2017 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>/features/going-ultralight-1</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/features/going-ultralight-1</guid>
        
        <category>features</category>
        
        
        <category>Features</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Sunix 120 Headtorch Review</title>
        <description>&lt;dl&gt;
  &lt;dt&gt;Pros&lt;/dt&gt;
  &lt;dd&gt;Rechargeable&lt;/dd&gt;
  &lt;dd&gt;Useful Modes&lt;/dd&gt;
  &lt;dd&gt;Compact&lt;/dd&gt;
  &lt;dd&gt;Long battery life&lt;/dd&gt;
  &lt;dt&gt;Cons&lt;/dt&gt;
  &lt;dd&gt;Comes loose easily&lt;/dd&gt;
  &lt;dd&gt;No over head strap&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I bought this Sunix headtorch from Amazon.co.uk in the summer of 2015 for roughly £16, I have used it almost daily since that time while jogging, camping and hiking at night.  I chose this headtorch mainly because it was the cheapest rechargeable headtorch I could find, but since purchase the durability and performance of the product has constantly surprised me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/sunnix/head.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Modes for all occasions, outstanding battery life and an incredibly reasonable pricepoint make up for the flimsy feel appearance and feel.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;build-quality&quot;&gt;Build Quality&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The standard of the materials used in the construction point to an origin somewhere in China, that is to say they aren’t the highest quality; the strap feels like very cheap plastic, as does the headtorch itself.  After some Googling I found that “Sunix” doesn’t appear to have a website, and the same model can be seen branded as a “Shuofang Spower” elsewhere.  This probably means that you shouldn’t expect much to come from the lifetime warranty guaranteed on the Amazon page, but the good news is that it seems to function well enough that you shouldn’t need to find out!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The LEDs, buttons, water-resistant seals, charging port and peripheral bag and charging cable are all of acceptable, if somewhat lacking quality, but nothing has broken in two years of near constant use.  I have exposed the IPX 6 sealing of the unit to many a rain, sleet and snow shower while jogging and hiking, but nothing seems to have penetrated, and the LEDs are still working.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/sunnix/front.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;The unit looks quite nice while remaining functional; the button is large enough to operate easily even with thick gloves on.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;design&quot;&gt;Design&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The physical design of the unit is fairly nice, the single button gives a satisfying click and springy response, navigating the modes with different clicking patterns is very easy indeed, as well as being simple enough to memorise straight away.  For me, the one thing the design is missing is an over head strap, just to make it that bit more secure, because the lateral strap can works itself loose quite fast when you’re running.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The unit features a bright, 120 lumen spotlight mode, with a 50 lumen floodlight setting for normal use around camp, both of these can be set to strobe with three successive button clicks.  The red night light mode is bright enough to  perform any tasks around camp without ruining your night vision, a must for any stargazers, and very handy if the inside of your tent is white or reflective.  There are also charging and over-discharging warning lights to let you know when you might be damaging the life of the battery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m constantly surprised by the length of burn time I can get out of the battery, if I use it an hour a day jogging in the evening, with the odd camp thrown in, I probably charge it once every 2 months, sometimes longer.  The provided 4 inch micro USB charging cable weighs roughly 10 grams so you can carry it everywhere, just in case you need a boost on the trail.  Micro USB means you can pack just one cable to charge your phone and headtorch!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/sunnix/charge.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;A full charge takes around 30 minutes, mine tends to go a month or two between charges when I use it for an hour a night for jogging.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The torch, strap and charging cable all pack down to a handy pocket sized lump in the provided black dry bag.  Everything packed weighs only 119 grams (4.2 ounces) so it’s no hassle to throw in any coat or bag, even on longer trips.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/sunnix/pack.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;If you squash it into a coat pocket, the whole lot will compress down to a 3&quot; x 3&quot; ball.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;alternatives&quot;&gt;Alternatives&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alternatives to the Sunix 120 within the same price range seem to be either unbranded cheap tat, require normal AAA batteries, require you to buy separate rechargeable batteries or weigh a lot more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Petzl are generally regarded as the top dog in the world of headtorches but that comes with a bump in price, the Petzl Tikka matches the functionality of the Sunix but you’ll have to drop a further £20 on top of the ~£20 unit cost if you want a rechargeable battery pack.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;final-thoughts&quot;&gt;Final Thoughts&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Sunix, although a bit tacky on first impressions, is astonishingly good value for what is a very handy and feature-laden item.  It’s served me well over nearly two years of jogging in all weather as well as being handy to read by in a tent.  I don’t think you can find a better headtorch for less than £25, let alone £16, it’s the outdoor gear holy grail; light, compact, cheap, reliable, convenient.  I have since bought a second one for my father to use in the garage/under cars, he is sold on it too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;rating-44&quot;&gt;Rating: 4/4&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At this price, this is the best head torch I’ve seen.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 28 Mar 2017 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>/reviews/sunix-review</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/reviews/sunix-review</guid>
        
        <category>reviews</category>
        
        
        <category>Reviews</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>How to Camp Out by John Mead Gould</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;The first book to be featured as Boldly Goes’ outdoor book of the month is one of the first books written about recreational camping.  ‘How to Camp Out’ was written in 1877 by American Civil War veteran John Mead Gould, he wanted to popularise recreational hiking and camping, and especially inspire the young of the USA to go out and experience what they could while they were able.  I read the entire guide in a single sitting and made notes of interesting techniques and notable quotes as I went, finishing with quite a long list.  The book definitely succeeded in inspiring me to get outside and make the most of my youth, I immediately put some of the skills I had read of in practice and began to take Gould’s advice on note taking very seriously.  It is part of the reason I wanted to start Boldly Goes to begin with and you will no doubt see me quote its timeless wisdom in future articles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style=&quot;font-style: italic; font-weight: 800; font-size: 18px;&quot;&gt;
&quot;Consequently, write what you can, and let it stand with all its blots, errors, and nonsense. And be careful, when you are five years older, not to go through the diary with eraser and scissors; for, if you live still another five years, nothing will interest you more than this diary with all its defects.&quot;   &lt;br /&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-style: italic; font-weight: 400; font-size: 14px;&quot;&gt; - John M. Gould&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The preface really tells you everything you need to know about this book; it summarises the advice of a very experienced outdoorsman with the intention of inspiring the young people of the USA to go out and experience everything nature has to offer.  Gould does this by systematically providing all of the information they would need to assemble a travelling party of their own and survive outdoors for an extended period of time.  This includes a briefing on all of the important aspects of camping, from  which equipment to buy and how to cook on an open fire  to advice on how to take useful notes on your trip, with a view to write them up for posterity later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The book continues with 11 chapters detailing everything the youth of 1877 needed to know to prepare and set out into the, then very, wild American countryside.  He begins with the preparations you might need to make before you leave and recommends leaving all but the essentials behind to save pack weight.  Then he moves on through the equipment and tasks which you’ll be using and performing when camping and provides a quick but thorough summary of best practises to prepare you.  Very few people will find it useful know know about loading a pack onto a horse and cart then walking next to it up a mountain these days, but these less applicable snippets provide a window into outdoor life in the 1800s, they have a different value.  This is the beauty of Gould’s guide; it contains a lot of techniques that remain the same today, and anything outdated provides an insight into the history of camping and hiking, there are no wasted chapters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His words on the versatility of a wool rug inspired me to drag our old family wool blend picnic rug from the car and give it a go, I was pleasantly surprised to find it was extremely useful in the woods where the Boldly Goes team usually camps.  Rolled up and slung over the shoulder, it’s a comfortable, if a bit warm, way to carry clothes and food.  Folded it provides a nice seat or sleeping mat in the summer, and it stops the wind wicking away the warmth from your sleeping bag when wrapped around it.  It’s obviously a bit heavy, but if you’re camping overnight and aren’t walking too far, it’s definitely a nice thing to have.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/marchbotm/rug.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;As well as keep you warm in the evenings, a wool rug makes carrying extra food and water a breeze.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the final two chapters of the book, Gould has included extracts in full from the work of two other experts of the day.  The first, Reverend Edward Everett Hale, has some insights into the habits you should develop while hiking as well as a cautionary tale on not taking chances of adventure when they present themselves.  The second, Dr. Elliott Coues, offers advice on avoiding injury and illness outdoors, the preventative measures like keeping warm and always maintaining three points of contact when climbing still ring true.  I would, however, advise finding some more up-to-date information on reviving a drowned man that doesn’t involve rubbing their face to make it warm, them splashing cold water on it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style=&quot;font-style: italic; font-weight: 800; font-size: 18px;&quot;&gt; &quot;Be independent, but not impudent. See all you can, and make the most of your time; &quot;time is money;&quot; and, when you grow older, you may find it even more difficult to command time than money.&quot; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-style: italic; font-weight: 400; font-size: 14px;&quot;&gt; - John M. Gould&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How to Camp Out is 70 pages of distilled knowledge written in an accessible way by a man whose clear love for the outdoors and passion for teaching others shines throughout the book, making it a pleasure to read.  It’s a lovely little piece of nourishing history which I’d definitely recommend to keen outdoorsmen who are beginners or seasoned experts.  Both will come away from the book having learned different things: the newer, perhaps some new techniques and tips; the more experienced, some perspective on their outdoor skills and gear, and how little the basics have changed in 140 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How to Camp Out is available for free as an ebook or PDF via the &lt;a href=&quot;http://archive.org/stream/howtocampout17575gut/17575.txt&quot;&gt;Gutenberg project&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.gutenberg.org/files/17575/17575-h/17575-h.htm&quot;&gt;archive.org&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 24 Mar 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>/features/how-to-camp-out</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/features/how-to-camp-out</guid>
        
        <category>features</category>
        
        
        <category>Features</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Hot tent camping on a shoestring</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Hot tent camping is where a stove is used inside of the tent to provide warmth in extremely cold conditions. “Crikey!” I hear you cry, “That sounds mighty dangerous!”. That’s because you’re right. We’ve obviously got two very clear hazards here:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Risk of perishing in a raging inferno, and;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Slowly succumbing to the odourless persuasions of carbon monoxide&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Addressing point number one, any hot tent camping setup needs to be carefully designed to reduce the risk of fire hazard by ensuring there is no contact with flammable materials and that the stove is stable, and will not topple. The fire also needs to be carefully monitored at all times.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On point number two, the stove needs to have a good draw, ensuring that when it is in operation, noxious fumes are safely extracted out of the tent. Still, a downdraught is always a risk, therefore the only safe option here is that the fire must be completely extinguished when you go to sleep.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;If any readers are seriously considering hot tent camping we recommend doing your research and taking all the necessary precautions when dealing with fire in a confined space. What we are demonstrating in this article is a proof-of-concept of what can be achieved with not that much money.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In our &lt;a href=&quot;/features/beer-fire-and-power-tools&quot;&gt;previous article&lt;/a&gt; we discussed the construction of a mini wood burning stove made out of a beer keg. To use this in a hot tent camping setup we needed to make a couple of alterations. Namely the addition of longer chimney to extend through a hole in the tent. However, when we were testing our creation we found that the chimney became red hot. If this part came into contact with tent fabric, it would obviously be bad news. So we devised a two layer chimney; we stacked a number of old baked bean cans on top of each other then put a piece of aluminum tubing over the top.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/hot/1-full.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Full of beans&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the tent Sam picked up a vintage 1974 Polish Military issue lavvu for less than £30. If you’re not aware, the lavvu is a fantastic thing indeed. A lavvu consists of two large canvas ponchos and several pieces of aluminium tubing which can be combined to make a teepee. The ponchos have one hole on either side for each arm. When fully constructed, this leaves a convenient chimney sized hole in the lavvu.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/hot/2-chimney.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Erected lavvu with protruding chimney&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even though we used the aforementioned two layer chimney construction we still wanted to make sure the chimney did not come into contact with the lavvu canvas. To ensure this, we wedged the opening into a rigid diamond shape using a stiff twig either side of the chimney. Let’s just take a short break to admire the glorious dying light in our chosen camping location.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/hot/3-shep.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Shepherd&#39;s delight&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, back to burning stuff. We collected some firewood, loaded the mini keg stove and built another fire nearby also. As day became night, we lit the stove and closely monitored our creation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/hot/4-cosy.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Cosy living quarters&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the fire had got going all three of us piled into the lavvu, closed the door and basked in the intense heat quickly building in the small space. We found that the rough seal of the canvas lavvu massively helps to keep the heat from escaping and that within a matter of seconds of closing the door, the space became quite toasty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/hot/5-complete.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;The completed lavvu / mini tent hot camping set up&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whilst we didn’t sleep in the lavvu on the first night, I think we have proven that you can quite cheaply assemble a small, functional hot tent camping setup that could serve the purpose of quickly warming you up for a very small fuel load.  We’ll definitely be experimenting with this set up in the future. Breaking down the cost…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Beer keg ~ £15&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sheet aluminum ~£2&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aluminium chimney ~£10&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lavvu with aluminium poles ~£30&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Total: ~£57&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll leave you with a wonderful long exposure shot that James took of a passing plane in the night sky.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;large&quot;&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/hot/6-sky.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Night trails&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 10 Mar 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>/features/hot-tenting</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/features/hot-tenting</guid>
        
        <category>features</category>
        
        
        <category>Features</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Beer, fire and power tools</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;The team will soon be experimenting with a different kind of camping, Hot Tent Camping. Don’t worry, we aren’t planning on restarting the Carry On… franchise. Hot tent camping involves the use of a stove to provide warmth to the tent in particularly cold conditions. It is most often used for semi permanent setups in permanently cold conditions such as way up in North Canada. In these types of setups, specialist equipment is absolutely essential, eh. Amongst such equipment is typically a large and predictably heavy log burning stove.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re not a group to go spending money on expensive equipment where it isn’t warranted, especially if it’s for some crackpot idea that might only be a one time use. So, we went about making our own prototype, of sorts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The product spec was simple: up-cycle materials to make a small, lightweight, portable log burning stove with a chimney which can be attached to a hole in the camping canopy. We got thinking, what would be a good size item for the main chamber? We needed to find something which could take the heat of a 250°C fire, was fairly light and just the right size; not too big, not too small. Our solution was found in another one of the team’s shared hobbies, drinking beer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many supermarkets and microbreweries sell mini kegs which hold around 5 litres of beer. We wagered that one of these would be ideal as the starting point and first building block for our lightweight stove.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/beer/1-plan.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;A plan is made&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With a plethora of spare materials and some roughly sketched plans we would have promptly begun construction, except for one small problem. Our mini beer keg was still full of beer. Fortunately, with the help of my dad (whom was kindly providing use of workshop and many provisions), that issue was swiftly resolved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/beer/2-sam.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Sam (not my dad)&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, we needed to make a hole in the top of the keg to make room for a chimney. Looking at the wide selection of tools available to us we chose our weapon and quickly found that the stainless steel keg cut like butter at the hands of most sharp edges, especially a quickly oscillating jigsaw blade. After drilling several pilot holes we cut an opening in the top and folded in the lips. Following our theme of a low budget scrapheap challenge, we then inserted our next part, an old baked bean can for the chimney. After some gentle coercion this fit as snug as a bug in a rug.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/beer/3-can.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;This can can&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next, we needed to cut a hole and make some kind of door mechanism which would be simple to make but also easy to place and remove when the stove is burning away. The team sketched up a few different ideas and eventually settled upon the idea of placing a door, consisting of an appropriately shaped piece of sheet aluminium, on a small lip at the top of an opening.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/beer/4-hole.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Holely satisfying&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We then gutted the belly of the beast, drilling out the dispenser nozzle and several ventilation holes around the bottom, which would hopefully provide some draw of air. We also cut out the aluminum door and attached some wire to act as hook. Finally we cut out and bent some strips of aluminium to act as stage to hold the firewood above the bottom of the keg.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/beer/5-finished.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;The finished Article&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I swear that whenever the Boldly Goes team gets together, we end up making a fire; this occasion was no exception. We loaded the mini-keg stove with paper and kindling, lit the fire and put on the door. Within a minute the fire was roaring and an impressive draw was pulling the flame out the top of the old baked bean can chimney. We kept adding more kindling to the fire and quickly found that we had made a very hungry little stove indeed; it will tear through its maximum capacity of kindling in about five minutes flat. After which, the stove is quickly cool to the touch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/beer/6-safe.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;This will be totally safe in a tent, right?&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We burnt the stove for about 20 minutes in an attempt to burn off any of the paint or surface finishes on the keg which may produce noxious fumes. Investigating the state of the stove after it had cooled down we’d found that it had adopted a rustic blackened tinge inside and out. We also found that our aluminum fire stage inside had not survived the intense heat of the fire and had curled away to a thin wisp. Considering our creation and testing fairly successful, we’re now ready to incorporate this into a &lt;a href=&quot;/features/hot-tenting&quot;&gt;hot tent setup. &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 09 Mar 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>/features/beer-fire-and-power-tools</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/features/beer-fire-and-power-tools</guid>
        
        <category>features</category>
        
        
        <category>Features</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Soloventuring: Taking on your first solo trip</title>
        <description>&lt;div class=&quot;bg-scroll&quot; style=&quot;background-image: url(&#39;/media/img/solovent/1-derwent-water.jpg&#39;)&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Preparing for your first solo wild-camping trip can be a little daunting but the rewards in the long run can be great. I still clearly remember my first time solo camping. I was cycling from London to Edinburgh and had pitched up in a secluded spot behind a small church in Norfolk; that night every creak and rustle sounded like the creeping footsteps of some lurking murderer. I was petrified. Needless to say, I didn’t get much rest that night. Since that first time wild camping alone I have come to enjoy venturing out alone and actually really look forward to it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/solovent/2-tarp-tent.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Obviously my fears were a little irrational and the reality of the situation was a lot safer than I had given credence to. Logically, I think anyone would agree that walking down a city street at night is far more risky than wild-camping alone in a rural area somewhere, yet most of us would be much more comfortable facing the former than the latter. Fortunately, overcoming this logical-lapse really is just a matter of experience. A few times out under the stars on your own and you should start to feel a little more at ease and before you know it you’ll be confident heading out on solo adventures whenever the need calls you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re wondering at this point why the hell you’d ever want to head out into the wilderness alone here’s five reasons I’d give to persuade you to give it a try sometime:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p style=&quot;font-weight: bold&quot;&gt;Digital Detox &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you are anything like me, you probably spend too much time looking at screens, whether it’s at work or at home. Many of us spend our lives in a state of hyper-connection, checking what our friends are up to, what’s happening in the news, and binge watching the latest netflix hit show from the minute we wake up to the minute we go to bed. Get outside, lose signal, and relax.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p style=&quot;font-weight: bold&quot;&gt;Challenge yourself&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Trying something new and getting out of our comfort zone is something we all know we’re supposed to do but it’s easy to get wrapped up in the day-to-day and before you know it life has become like a real-life Groundhog day. A microadventure is an easy way to reboot. Choose somewhere beautiful, throw caution to the wind, pack your bags and go.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p style=&quot;font-weight: bold&quot;&gt;Be Independent&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Do your feet hurt? Stop walking. Are you hungry? Eat. Have you found a view you want to stop and take in? Take all the time you need. Spotted an interesting detour? Go. When you travel solo you are the master of your own destiny. No one can tell you what to do and there is no need to negotiate plans, you are free to go where you want and at whatever pace you like. Independence is freedom.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p style=&quot;font-weight: bold&quot;&gt;Finding Solitude&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Living in solitude for longs periods of time can be unhealthy and is certainly undesirable as us Humans are inherently sociable creatures. However, finding solitude once in awhile can actually be beneficial to your creativity and sense of personal identity. For hundreds of years religious types like them monks have used solitude to bolster their spirituality (so there’s that, if that sort of thing floats your boat).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p style=&quot;font-weight: bold&quot;&gt;Appreciating Nature&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Without sounding too hippy-ish, travelling alone can be rewarding in that you feel a little more connected to the environment around you. You’ll have plenty of time to take in the sights and sounds of your surroundings on your solo trip. Something that always gives me great pleasure is the moment when I pause on a summer cycle and the sound of the whirring tyres on tarmac and the clanking gears give way to sound of skylarks in the fields and the breeze through the trees. Ok, I’m getting a little sentimental but you get the idea!&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/solovent/3-camping-setup.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;My favourite camping setup, taken at my local woods, summer 2016&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My most recent Soloventure was into the hills and mountains of the English Lake District; a stunningly beautiful place that I really ought to visit more often. I made a quick plan and hopped in the car and punched ‘Keswick’ into my satnav. Four hours later I had arrived at my destination. I grabbed some supplies from the shop and was on my way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/solovent/4-crags.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;My camp spot at Dale Head Tarn, Oct 16&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I headed up the popular summit of Cat Bells and kept walking. I passed High Spy and descended into the saddle beneath Dale Head. This wasn’t any expeditionary feat, in fact the hike was fairly easy and not particularly long. I had considered staying in a Youth Hostel when I had made my initial plan for the day but I found an old and decrepit sheepfold beside a small tarn that looked a perfect place to set up camp. I unstrapped my bag and set up my tent. It’s worth noting here that although wild camping in the lakes is technically illegal - like anywhere else in England, it is de facto that once above the highest drystone walls wild-camping is permitted. Obviously I followed the same principles I would for any camp: leave no trace, arrive late and leave early, and be generally respectful. Normally when camping  I’d would like to have a fire but in the Lake District this is strictly forbidden and should be avoided.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next day I headed down the hill and after a leisurely walk along the shores of Derwent Water I was soon in my car and headed for home. It had been a great trip, super simple, super cheap, and very satisfying and completed in just 24 hours. I would recommend it to anyone. Next time you feel a little at odds with your work/life balance, looking for spiritual enlightenment, or simply all your adventure buddies are busy, why not take a Soloventure and see for yourself how good it is!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More photos from my Lake district Soloventure:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;album&quot;&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;
        &lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/solovent/album/scrolling-1.jpg&quot; /&gt;

    &lt;/figure&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;
        &lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/solovent/album/scrolling-2.jpg&quot; /&gt;

    &lt;/figure&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;
        &lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/solovent/album/scrolling-3.jpg&quot; /&gt;

    &lt;/figure&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;
        &lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/solovent/album/scrolling-4.jpg&quot; /&gt;

    &lt;/figure&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;
        &lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/solovent/album/scrolling-5.jpg&quot; /&gt;

    &lt;/figure&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;
        &lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/solovent/album/scrolling-6.jpg&quot; /&gt;

    &lt;/figure&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;
        &lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/solovent/album/scrolling-7.jpg&quot; /&gt;

    &lt;/figure&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;
        &lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/solovent/album/scrolling-8.jpg&quot; /&gt;

    &lt;/figure&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;
        &lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/solovent/album/scrolling-9.jpg&quot; /&gt;

    &lt;/figure&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;
        &lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/solovent/album/scrolling-10.jpg&quot; /&gt;

    &lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 01 Mar 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>/features/soloventures</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/features/soloventures</guid>
        
        <category>features</category>
        
        
        <category>Features</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>24 hours: in the New Forest</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/newf/1-mushroom.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was one of those deceptive October days where you can easily fool yourself for a moment that the summer might forget to end. After all, the sun was still high and bright and the trees were still thick with green leaves as we trundled down the M25, waiting in line for the M3 exit. This wasn’t the case everywhere. We had strategically avoided Norfolk where we had originally planned to go that weekend as the weather report that morning had showed what looked, to me at least, a lot like a small hurricane residing over the very stretch of coast we were headed for. And as intrepid as we certainly are it looked to be the making of a miserable time. So after a quick look online and few texts later we were in the car and on our way to the New Forest with only a faintest outline of a plan and missing a few adventurer’s-essentials, such as a map and food, for instance. The Scouts’ Motto ‘Be Prepared’; once the ever present and sage aphorism was by now just a distant echo in the back of my mind. But, hey, at least it was sunny.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/newf/2-ferrari.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We arrived up in the pretty village of Lyndhurst, my little red Mitsubishi looking at little out of place alongside the line of Ferrari’s and Maserati’s parked outside Meridien Modena, the sports car dealership on the village’s High street, but it was at least matching the colour scheme. The necessary items we required were easily found in the local shops and so we set off towards the forest now armed with an OS map and stocked up with beer and venison sausages. We walked due south and peeled off into a small estate of 60s-built suburban houses and down a cul-de-sac which would humbly serve as our gateway into what was once the hunting ground of choice for William the Conqueror.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/newf/3-sunrise.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The trees rose up high on either side of us. Instantly the air was colder and the once-wide open blues skies of Hampshire where now reduced to the narrow void between the trees created by the broad path. There was a tangible sense that there is something special about the New Forest, perhaps it came from just how much life there is everywhere around you as you walk. The forest’s trees consist of ancient stands of burled and burly Oaks and Beeches standing in tall and elegant poses, and younger tracts of Silver Birch and Pine. And it is true that in the Autumn it is near-impossible to find a patch of ground that isn’t home to one of the thousands of fungi species the live here in symbiosis with the forest’s plants and trees. The forest floor is alive with colourful mushrooms, from the bright red and instantly recognisable Fly Agaric, to the myriad species of stout and chunky Boletus, and the much sought after golden-capped Chanterelle. Combine all of this with wild roaming ponies and you begin to build a picture of the New Forest in all it’s mythic splendour.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/newf/4-ponies.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We searched for a spot to camp, somewhere out of sight and quiet where we could pitch up without disturbing any wildlife. The ground here is very wet is covered with a thick carpet of sphagnum, and any deadwood we could find was rotten and completely useless as firewood. It was clear that a campfire was out of the question and so we cooked up a sausage stew on a the camp stove and drank our beers under the light of the moon. The night was full of noises, from the familiar and comforting hoots of Tawny Owls to the once haunting pained-barks of foxes, a sound all wild-campers become accustomed to, as well as some hoarse mammalian howls that I’ve never before heard or since.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We rose, well rested, to a perfect morning. The air was crisp and the sun’s golden light was spilling through the leaves of the trees. The forest had welcomed and rewarded us with its natural beauty and simplicity but it was now sadly time to leave and return to normality. We packed our kit away and took our path back to Lyndhurst, taking in once more the sheer loveliness of our host.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We stopped for espresso’s and bruschetta before hitting the road at an independent cafe, choosing to sit outside in the sunshine. We looked in that moment both cosmopolitan and disheveled, as if we were the latest incarnation of hipster, amping-up the lumberjack look to full-blown woodland tramp. Little did our passers-by know of our microadventure in the woods; our little slice of solitude far away from the complexities of modern life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the drive home I noticed that just a few of the leaves on the trees had started to show the first signs of oranging and loosening themselves from their branches. It seemed the seasons had hinged on our weekend. And just as one began to close another came into the fore, putting to rest the last hopes that the summer may just linger on in act of happy forgetfulness.             &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/newf/5-sunrise.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/newf/6-tarp.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/newf/7-beer.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/newf/8-mushroom.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 18 Feb 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>/features/24-newforest</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/features/24-newforest</guid>
        
        <category>microadventures</category>
        
        <category>mushrooms</category>
        
        <category>camping</category>
        
        
        <category>Features</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Photo Story: Edinburgh to Stornorway</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;My odyssey from the Scottish capital to the northern reaches of its Western Isles&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-plan&quot;&gt;1. The Plan&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/edstor/1-plan.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My chosen route for my cycle touring trip from Edinburgh to the the top of the Outer Hebrides islands back in the summer of 2015.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-means&quot;&gt;2. The Means&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/edstor/2-means.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is my rig for my ride from Edinburgh to the Outer Hebrides islands. If you’re not one for nerdy bike talk I recommend moving on now. You’ve been warned. This is my Kona Honkytonk, I know, I know, why didn’t you get the Kona Sutra, I hear you cycle-touring pros out there say. Well, I really would have preferred the Sutra but I couldn’t find it anywhere for less than £1200 and so finding this, a bike I had ridden before and liked a lot for £500 brand-new was really a no-brainer. It has a steel frame, heavy but strong and easily repairable compared to aluminium frames, and it looks great. I went for the tried-and-tested Ortlieb panniers and Brook’s saddle and just looked away from the laptop screen as I pressed the ‘use all your savings to buy this’ button. They are fantastic though.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I changed a few items for this trip to Scotland such as the tyres, I went for Schwalbe Marathons. Sure, they’re heavy but I can’t tell you the peace of mind afforded to you knowing that your chances of a puncture are reduced to almost nothing. In fact I didn’t get a single puncture during my trip and even gave away most of my repair kit to a fellow cycle tourer who had endless flats. I also removed the clip-in pedals and replaced them with cheapo flat pedals with the reasoning that I could wear more comfortable shoes while riding and that speed didn’t really matter anyway. Jury’s still out on whether this was really a good idea! I could go on a lot more about the rig but I appreciate we all have lives to live!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;leaving-home&quot;&gt;3. Leaving Home&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/edstor/3-leaving.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
Stevenage train station, packed and ready for the 5 hour train ride to Edinburgh.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;welcome-to-scotland&quot;&gt;4. Welcome to Scotland&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/edstor/4-welcome.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
The superb Forth railway bridge. I could at this point provide some highly dubious trivia, regarding how it’s always in the process of being painted, but I’ll spare you. The bridge I’m stood on in this picture, however, appears to be slowly falling apart. They have installed acoustic listening devices on the suspension cables to listen for the pings of breaking strands of steel, just to keep an eye on things. Reassuring.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;unexpected-adventures&quot;&gt;5. Unexpected Adventures&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/edstor/5-unexpected.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
What’s great about Scotland is that you can camp anywhere, more or less. On my first night I found a quiet and secluded meadow that looked perfect. The sky was clear and the stars were out so I opted for the bivvy bag - wild camping at it’s best if you ask me! However, what I had failed to realise was that this meadow was part of an active construction site. The sound of reversing sirens are a lot louder than the alarm on my phone and went off quite a bit earlier too! An exchange of thumb’s-up was had and I was soon on my way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;new-aquaintances&quot;&gt;6. New Aquaintances&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/edstor/6-new.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
I’m sure by this point you’re beginning to see that the main character of my trip was my trusty steed, Honky. What I don’t have, sadly, is many pictures of all the people I met on the way. Whilst heading through the Highlands towards Oban I met Colin from Wyoming who had been travelling across Europe and was on his final leg, cycling in Scotland. We were headed in the same direction for the next 50 miles or so, so we buddied up for the day. We stayed at a campsite that night and enjoyed a good night’s drinking down the local. The next day, a little sore-headed, we bid each other farewell and went on our separate ways.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;crossing-the-minch&quot;&gt;7. Crossing the Minch&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/edstor/7-crossing.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
From Oban it was a 5 hour ferry ride to Lochboisdale, which I spent with a fellow cycle tourer; an Aberdeen girl who was headed for Barra. The boat ride had it’s up’s and down’s, every 15 seconds or so, in a relentless swaying motion. I have never seen so much vomit. My companion had assured me she’d inherited an iron stomach from a long line of seafarer’s, the look on her face as she slowly made her way through the ferry canteens mac’n’cheese told a different story.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;night-rider&quot;&gt;8. Night-rider&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/edstor/8-night.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
I arrived on the Western Isles shortly after 11 to a pitch-black night. I put my lights on and cycled into the night. This was to be one of the best rides of my life, in complete darkness surrounded by the ethereal whirring of burrowing Puffins and the whistling wind. I cycled for a long way into the night until a car pulled up next to me. I was certain I had met my final bloody fate. The window of the car wound down and before appeared not an axe-wielding maniac looking for nocturnal cyclists but a friendly faced middle-aged woman. She asked me where I was headed, to which I replied ‘that way’, to which she said ‘there isn’t anything that way’. She recommended that I find a camp spot soon before heading into what was just squidgy swamps and pools for miles. She drove on and I set my bivvy up in the bus shelter a few yards up the road. This, unsurprisingly a poor place to camp, as I was the unwelcome visitor to what was already the home for every creepy crawly in the local vicinity. The morning light came as a relief. It also revealed my environment for the first time. A sparse, mostly treeless landscape with short rugged hills and endless tiny lochs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;a-sign-of-things-to-come&quot;&gt;9. A Sign of Things to Come&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/edstor/9-sign.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
Loved these signs, at a glance it looks like a dinosaur, Nessie even. Kept my eyes peeled for otters (and Nessie) but had no such luck.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;french-fried&quot;&gt;10. French-fried&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/edstor/10-french.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
These two french cyclists had spent the previous two days cycling together and went their separate ways not long after this picture was taken but not before sharing a wee dram of whisky and baileys too, plus a few tokes on our new friend’s jazz cigarette. Afterwards we all had a go at riding about recklessly on his recumbent bike, attempting to do skids in the middle of an A-road.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;crofting-on-berneray-island&quot;&gt;11. Crofting on Berneray Island&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/edstor/11-crofting.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
This is the Youth Hostel on the island of Berneray. On the way I passed by a village hall with a free wifi and by this point internet and phone signal had become a luxury, so I headed inside. I was met by an English couple. I politely asked if I could have the password, ‘Of course you can dear’ the lady said, ‘would you like to learn about the island’s history first?’, if only I had the courage to say no. I patiently leafed through binders of sepia photographs of stern faced school masters, fishermen, and priests, only to be told after a long history lesson that the internet was in fact down. Great! ‘But don’t worry,’ she said, ‘between you and me, the B-and-B down the road has a Wifi network with no password.’ I promised to keep my word and headed to the b-and-b, where sure enough I got some slow but usable free Wifi.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;psycho-killer&quot;&gt;12. Psycho Killer&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/edstor/12-psycho.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
Every hosteller’s worst nightmare: the axe-murderer, seen here moments before dealing the fatal blow. Thankfully this was not a real axe murderer but a fellow friendly traveller. That night there were a few of us staying in the old white-washed croft. Later in the evening a crusty old pirate-looking fellow turned up asking us if we wanted to buy some crab meat. Two young, and mute (up to this point) Italian sisters, looking a bit bewildered by their situation, piped up and took some of the crab from the man’s hamper. They had, however, misunderstood that the man would be expecting some recompense for his efforts and wasn’t just driving around doling out crab for nothing and so they shyly returned the crab. The man got very angry and huffed loudly the words ‘fucking timewasters’ before slamming the door, leaving his Jack Russell staring out through the window as his master trundled off in his old Rav4. It was scary, and we suspected he may be our axe-murderer. In the end his dog wandered off and we all woke up with the standard number of limbs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;harris-home-of-tweed&quot;&gt;13. Harris, Home of Tweed&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/edstor/13-harris.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
The next day I arrived on the Isle of Harris famous for it’s tweed. In fact, the Isle of Harris and the Isle of Lewis are indeed the same island, the only thing separating them being their geography, Lewis is largely flat and bleak, and Harris has some large, more Highland-like hills and mountains. You can see in the picture here a glimpse of the Hebrides’ famous white sands and aquamarine seas. If I could do this again I would allow myself more time to explore the beautiful beaches here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;rr&quot;&gt;14. R+R&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/edstor/14-rr.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
It took me a long time to get back on the road after staying at the youth hostel in Rhenigidale, partly because it served such luxuries as this wood-burning stove and a DAB radio, but mostly because I knew would have to cycle up and over a mountain I had to cycle over to get here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;facing-the-inevitable&quot;&gt;15. Facing the Inevitable&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/edstor/15-facing.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
Aforementioned mountain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;back-to-the-mainland&quot;&gt;16. Back to the Mainland&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/edstor/16-back.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
The next day took me to Stornoway where I spent the night in an overpriced hotel, ate pub food, drank beer, and watched TV. The journey across Lewis had been bleak with really not much to speak of other than the brief glimpse of a White-tailed Eagle. The next day I took the ferry to Ullapool, the crossing taking us past the pointed peaks of Skye and I offering sightings of dolphins as they leaped from the water beside the boat. I loaded my bike on to the bike bus in Ullapool which took me to Inverness where I was to catch the sleeper train back home the following day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;journeys-end&quot;&gt;17. Journey’s End.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/edstor/17-end.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
Dusk in Inverness on the final night of my trip. When I arrived at the station I was informed that there was no room for my bike on the train by an officious train guard standing in front of the mile-long Caledonian Sleeper train and that a courier would be driving it in a van to London. My whole experience on the sleeper was pretty dismal to be honest and I glad when it was over. Back in London I waited on a back street near Euston for a white van to turn up with my bike. A different man arrived from the one I’d handed my bike to in Scotland, and an hour late at that.  My annoyance was neutralised when I noticed he’d made his part of the journey through the night with his young child sleeping in the front of his van, I thanked him and cycled to Kings-Cross where I caught the train home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;album&quot;&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;
        &lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/edstor/album1.jpg&quot; /&gt;

    &lt;/figure&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;
        &lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/edstor/album2.jpg&quot; /&gt;

    &lt;/figure&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;
        &lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/edstor/album3.jpg&quot; /&gt;

    &lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 14 Feb 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>/features/cycling-scotland</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/features/cycling-scotland</guid>
        
        <category>cycling</category>
        
        <category>adventure</category>
        
        <category>photostories</category>
        
        
        <category>Features</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Jack Wolfskin Gossamer 1 Review</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Internal dimensions: Length 230cm, Height 70cm, Width 95cm&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Construction: PU coated 75D Polyester, Alloy poles and pegs&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Weight: 1550g&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pack size: 45cmx17cm&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;dl&gt;
  &lt;dt&gt;Pros&lt;/dt&gt;
  &lt;dd&gt;Great build quality&lt;/dd&gt;
  &lt;dd&gt;Striking design&lt;/dd&gt;
  &lt;dd&gt;Relatively cheap&lt;/dd&gt;
  &lt;dt&gt;Cons&lt;/dt&gt;
  &lt;dd&gt;Tough to pitch correctly&lt;/dd&gt;
  &lt;dd&gt;Damp problems&lt;/dd&gt;
  &lt;dd&gt;Limited storage&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/gossamer/cover.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;The Gossamer in all it&#39;s saggy glory.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I bought my Gossamer from OutdoorGear.co.uk for £75 last April, before the BoldlyGoes trip to Spain.  I initially chose it over the Wild Country Zephyros 1, due to it’s interesting design and £35 price difference. The two-pole tunnel design isn’t a popular tent design, but it looks great and pitching is a breeze, even in bad conditions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;build-quality&quot;&gt;Build Quality&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The build quality of the Gossamer is remarkably good, 10 months after purchase, and dozens of pitches later, all of the seams are still tight, the DAC poles are as good as new, and although I lost one peg, the others are all still straight despite quite a lot of abuse.  The one component which requires improvement is the ground sheet, which professes to have a 5,000mm hydrostatic head, but will let beads of moisture through by the morning.  The tent includes only 10 pegs while the design actually requires 12 including guy lines, but unless it’s very windy, these are optional.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/gossamer/pack.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;High quality materials and a small pack size make it attractive for backpackers.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;design&quot;&gt;Design&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The design of the Gossamer straddles the line between the low, compact, hooped bivvys and the roomier 1 man backpacking tents with room to sit up and porches to store your backpack.  This fusion results in a compromised experience, just entering the tent requires some thought, the door is at the head end rather than at the side, this requires you to stand up in the entrance, then filter yourself into the tent and your sleeping bag at the same time, feet first.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Gossamer has a large unsupported mid section, which ends up sagging however tight I pitch, this sag, seen in most hooped bivvys is not an issue with single walled gore-tex designs.  But coupled with the double walled design of the gossamer, this sag results in condensation soaking your clothes or sleeping bag after even the smallest movements during the night or morning.  This sag could be solved easily with two extra guy lines halfway up either side of the tent, but the curved design limits the options there without pulling the top of the tent flat.  Having pitched the tent in a number of ways, I can’t seem to adjust it to the point where there is a gap between the fly and the mesh inner.  This wouldn’t be a huge problem in a tent which was slightly larger, I’ve seen several larger double walled tents with no space between the fly and the inner, but if you roll over in your sleeping bag at night in those you won’t be touching the sides of the tent.  In a compact design like this one, it results in guarranteed dampness when you move around.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The lack of a porch or any storage space is an issue; there isn’t room for anything larger than a 35 litre backpack inside next to you, and only boots can be stored in between the two walls.  If you’re camping in colder weather or have a lot of gear with you, the only option is to stick the whole lot in a dry bag and leave it outside, not entirely secure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you are inside (and as long as you don’t move too much), the Gossamer is very cosy, the lack of space actually means it warms up very quickly.  There is a useful guy line running along the ceiling of the tent where you can hang lights, it also tensions the ceiling to stop a little bit of that lethal sag.  The low design lends itself to stability in high winds and the position of the side pegs does afford some control over the airflow into the tent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;alternatives&quot;&gt;Alternatives&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I’ve said, the Gossamer has slotted itself into a strange place in the market, where it finds itself competing with budget tents, more expensive entry level backpacking tents and most hooped bivvys.  My second choice when looking for a tent was the Wild Country Zephyros 1, this much roomier back packing tent features a porch, room to sit up and change and weighed slightly less, but it was £35 more expensive.  The Snugpak Stratosphere Hooped Bivi features a superior construction quality and materials, but had even less storage space and the same £35 price difference.  The Highlander Blackthorn 1 was the budget option at half the price of the Gossamer, has the same design as the now legendary Gelert Solo, but suffered from terrible build quality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;bg-scroll&quot; style=&quot;background-image: url(&#39;/media/img/gossamer/reverse.jpg&#39;)&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;final-thoughts&quot;&gt;Final Thoughts&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In conclusion, the Gossamer 1 would be a great first tent for anyone given its modest price tag, but it is let down by the lack of conviction in it’s design, or possibly it’s total conviction to not be like any other tent on the market. When I want to sit in my tent and watch the rain, I am forced to just get up like when I am bivvy bagging.  When I feel cosy and warm like in a bivvy bag, I get damp from the condensation like I am in a cramped tent.  It’s the best and worst of both worlds, but no one fault completely hampers the experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t regret the purchase and I can see it surviving at least two or three more seasons, it isn’t too heavy or bulky enough to put me off carrying it on longer hikes.  However, if it broke I would not buy it again, if I were buying a tent in the same price range again, I’d spend a little extra for the added comfort and gear security offered by the Wild Country Zephyros 1.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/gossamer/door.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;The Gossamer never finds it&#39;s stride, but it&#39;s still a well made starter tent.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;rating-24&quot;&gt;Rating: 2/4&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Entry level gear that we probably wouldn’t buy again if it broke.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 09 Feb 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>/reviews/gossamer-review</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/reviews/gossamer-review</guid>
        
        <category>reviews</category>
        
        <category>tents</category>
        
        <category>gear</category>
        
        
        <category>Reviews</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
