<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Boldly Goes</title>
    <description>Three lads from Hertfordshire entertain you with articles on outdoor topics.</description>
    <link>/</link>
    <atom:link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Mar 2017 22:49:51 +0000</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 01 Mar 2017 22:49:51 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.1.6</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Soloventuring: Taking on your first solo trip</title>
        <description>&lt;div class=&quot;bg-scroll&quot; style=&quot;background-image: url(&#39;/media/img/solovent/1-derwent-water.jpg&#39;)&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Preparing for your first solo wild-camping trip can be a little daunting but the rewards in the long run can be great. I still clearly remember my first time solo camping. I was cycling from London to Edinburgh and had pitched up in a secluded spot behind a small church in Norfolk; that night every creak and rustle sounded like the creeping footsteps of some lurking murderer. I was petrified. Needless to say, I didn’t get much rest that night. Since that first time wild camping alone I have come to enjoy venturing out alone and actually really look forward to it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/solovent/2-tarp-tent.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Obviously my fears were a little irrational and the reality of the situation was a lot safer than I had given credence to. Logically, I think anyone would agree that walking down a city street at night is far more risky than wild-camping alone in a rural area somewhere, yet most of us would be much more comfortable facing the former than the latter. Fortunately, overcoming this logical-lapse really is just a matter of experience. A few times out under the stars on your own and you should start to feel a little more at ease and before you know it you’ll be confident heading out on solo adventures whenever the need calls you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re wondering at this point why the hell you’d ever want to head out into the wilderness alone here’s five reasons I’d give to persuade you to give it a try sometime:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p style=&quot;font-weight: bold&quot;&gt;Digital Detox &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you are anything like me, you probably spend too much time looking at screens, whether it’s at work or at home. Many of us spend our lives in a state of hyper-connection, checking what our friends are up to, what’s happening in the news, and binge watching the latest netflix hit show from the minute we wake up to the minute we go to bed. Get outside, lose signal, and relax.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p style=&quot;font-weight: bold&quot;&gt;Challenge yourself&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Trying something new and getting out of our comfort zone is something we all know we’re supposed to do but it’s easy to get wrapped up in the day-to-day and before you know it life has become like a real-life Groundhog day. A microadventure is an easy way to reboot. Choose somewhere beautiful, throw caution to the wind, pack your bags and go.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p style=&quot;font-weight: bold&quot;&gt;Be Independent&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Do your feet hurt? Stop walking. Are you hungry? Eat. Have you found a view you want to stop and take in? Take all the time you need. Spotted an interesting detour? Go. When you travel solo you are the master of your own destiny. No one can tell you what to do and there is no need to negotiate plans, you are free to go where you want and at whatever pace you like. Independence is freedom.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p style=&quot;font-weight: bold&quot;&gt;Finding Solitude&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Living in solitude for longs periods of time can be unhealthy and is certainly undesirable as us Humans are inherently sociable creatures. However, finding solitude once in awhile can actually be beneficial to your creativity and sense of personal identity. For hundreds of years religious types like them monks have used solitude to bolster their spirituality (so there’s that, if that sort of thing floats your boat).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p style=&quot;font-weight: bold&quot;&gt;Appreciating Nature&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Without sounding too hippy-ish, travelling alone can be rewarding in that you feel a little more connected to the environment around you. You’ll have plenty of time to take in the sights and sounds of your surroundings on your solo trip. Something that always gives me great pleasure is the moment when I pause on a summer cycle and the sound of the whirring tyres on tarmac and the clanking gears give way to sound of skylarks in the fields and the breeze through the trees. Ok, I’m getting a little sentimental but you get the idea!&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/solovent/3-camping-setup.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;My favourite camping setup, taken at my local woods, summer 2016&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My most recent Soloventure was into the hills and mountains of the English Lake District; a stunningly beautiful place that I really ought to visit more often. I made a quick plan and hopped in the car and punched ‘Keswick’ into my satnav. Four hours later I had arrived at my destination. I grabbed some supplies from the shop and was on my way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/solovent/4-crags.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;My camp spot at Dale Head Tarn, Oct 16&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I headed up the popular summit of Cat Bells and kept walking. I passed High Spy and descended into the saddle beneath Dale Head. This wasn’t any expeditionary feat, in fact the hike was fairly easy and not particularly long. I had considered staying in a Youth Hostel when I had made my initial plan for the day but I found an old and decrepit sheepfold beside a small tarn that looked a perfect place to set up camp. I unstrapped my bag and set up my tent. It’s worth noting here that although wild camping in the lakes is technically illegal - like anywhere else in England, it is de facto that once above the highest drystone walls wild-camping is permitted. Obviously I followed the same principles I would for any camp: leave no trace, arrive late and leave early, and be generally respectful. Normally when camping  I’d would like to have a fire but in the Lake District this is strictly forbidden and should be avoided.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next day I headed down the hill and after a leisurely walk along the shores of Derwent Water I was soon in my car and headed for home. It had been a great trip, super simple, super cheap, and very satisfying and completed in just 24 hours. I would recommend it to anyone. Next time you feel a little at odds with your work/life balance, looking for spiritual enlightenment, or simply all your adventure buddies are busy, why not take a Soloventure and see for yourself how good it is!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More photos from my Lake district Soloventure:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;album&quot;&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;
        &lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/solovent/album/scrolling-1.jpg&quot; /&gt;

    &lt;/figure&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;
        &lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/solovent/album/scrolling-2.jpg&quot; /&gt;

    &lt;/figure&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;
        &lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/solovent/album/scrolling-3.jpg&quot; /&gt;

    &lt;/figure&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;
        &lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/solovent/album/scrolling-4.jpg&quot; /&gt;

    &lt;/figure&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;
        &lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/solovent/album/scrolling-5.jpg&quot; /&gt;

    &lt;/figure&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;
        &lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/solovent/album/scrolling-6.jpg&quot; /&gt;

    &lt;/figure&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;
        &lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/solovent/album/scrolling-7.jpg&quot; /&gt;

    &lt;/figure&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;
        &lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/solovent/album/scrolling-8.jpg&quot; /&gt;

    &lt;/figure&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;
        &lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/solovent/album/scrolling-9.jpg&quot; /&gt;

    &lt;/figure&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;
        &lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/solovent/album/scrolling-10.jpg&quot; /&gt;

    &lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 01 Mar 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>/features/soloventures</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/features/soloventures</guid>
        
        <category>features</category>
        
        
        <category>Features</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The road to a 10lb pack: The first step</title>
        <description>&lt;p style=&quot;text-align: center; font-size: 20px; font-weight: bold;&quot;&gt; Why go ultralight? When go ultralight? How go ultralight? &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;In this series I’ll be taking you through my thought process as I shaved the pounds off of my setup, taking it from a bloated giant which will drag me down with it, to a sleek ultralight bundle that I hardly notice as I skip along the cliffside like a mountain goat who’s just discovered weight watchers.  Hopefully you’ll find some tips that you can use with your gear, if you have any tips of your own, remember to share them in the comments!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Until now, the majority of my camping has involved setting up a base camp somewhere a few miles out from the car and day hiking to explore the surrounding area with only a day sack on my back.  Recently, however, I have planned a few more adventurous trips which will involve hiking and camping with everything on my back for two weeks or more, this is when lighter gear starts to seem very appealing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Being outside is great fun; hiking, cycling, canoeing, camping, these have all been enjoyed as past times since the 1800s when camping and hiking were first popularised.  Things can be made much less fun, however, if you are forced to carry enormous weight while you partake in them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Very few young men who read this book will find it possible to enjoy themselves, and carry more than twenty pounds a greater distance than ten miles a day, for a week.” 
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;b&gt;John Mead Gould in ‘How To Camp Out’&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That was written in 1877.  Twenty pounds was more than the advised limit when hiking recreationally for an american civil war veteran.  He was surely a lot tougher than you or I, probably a fair bit stronger, and even he didn’t carry a heavy pack back when everything was made from either wool or iron.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These days a pack base weight of around 20lbs will class you as a ‘lightweight’ backpacker, but if it was too heavy in 1877, it’s certainly too heavy for my flimsy millennial bones today.  A pack weighing 5lbs will apparently see you classified as a ‘super-ultralight’ or ‘hyperlight’ backpacker.  From what I have seen, this weight is where you enter the realms of record breaking, astonishingly fast hikers who blaze past you with no time to concentrate on the scenery or get a trail name that doesn’t involve a superlative.  These hikernators usually forgo every creature comfort they can to save weight, and eat only food with the highest of calorie to weight ratios.  Because I’m not keen on re-hydrated beans, and wouldn’t mind the odd cup of coffee on the trail, I’m going to aim for the middle ground. 10lbs. Ultralight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first step in lightening your load is also the easiest and certainly the cheapest; you just need to unpack everything and start from the beginning.  Starting from the bottom forces you to tackle everything you put into your pack; you’re looking at each item in a new light now, a revealing, minimalist, white light which isn’t flattering to anything but the essential.  You need to really think about how important everything is before you put it in your bag, and it’s likely even your bag could lose some weight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I repacked the first time, I picked up only the things which are directly linked to my survival outdoors; water, shelter and food.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Image before and after: Two images dide by side, one empty rucksack surrounded by all my things, one empty rucksack surrounded by the essentials.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is what my pack contains so far:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Water containers and water purification tablets - weight
&lt;br /&gt;
Tent and sleeping system (Sleeping bag and foam mat)
&lt;br /&gt;
My alcohol stove and pan set with spoon&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Notice that I’ve chosen simple re-usable plastic bottles for my water, a foam roll as a sleeping mat and will be eating from the one pot which I cook in.  This saves me the weight of a water bladder and hose, the heavy plastic of an inflatable sleeping mat, and a bowl or mug which I had been bringing to eat out of.  I’ve also chosen a simple plastic spoon which weighs 10 grams, over a more expensive, fancy titanium contraption from Amazon, because, it’s a spoon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note that you could also opt for a stoveless setup, but we’ll &lt;a href=&quot;https://boldlygoes.co.uk/features/ultralight-part-5&quot; title=&quot;Part 5&quot;&gt;get to that later&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now we have a base, base weight.  These items are the ones which probably aren’t going to change depending on the season or the amount of time we hike for. In the next part, we’ll look at the items which are going to vary depending on the season and weather during your time outdoors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://boldlygoes.co.uk/features/ultralight-part-2&quot; title=&quot;Part 2&quot;&gt;Part 2: Ultralight clothing&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 28 Feb 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>/features/ultralight-backpacking</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/features/ultralight-backpacking</guid>
        
        <category>features</category>
        
        
        <category>Features</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>24 hours: in the New Forest</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/newf/1-mushroom.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was one of those deceptive October days where you can easily fool yourself for a moment that the summer might forget to end. After all, the sun was still high and bright and the trees were still thick with green leaves as we trundled down the M25, waiting in line for the M3 exit. This wasn’t the case everywhere. We had strategically avoided Norfolk where we had originally planned to go that weekend as the weather report that morning had showed what looked, to me at least, a lot like a small hurricane residing over the very stretch of coast we were headed for. And as intrepid as we certainly are it looked to be the making of a miserable time. So after a quick look online and few texts later we were in the car and on our way to the New Forest with only a faintest outline of a plan and missing a few adventurer’s-essentials, such as a map and food, for instance. The Scouts’ Motto ‘Be Prepared’; once the ever present and sage aphorism was by now just a distant echo in the back of my mind. But, hey, at least it was sunny.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/newf/2-ferrari.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We arrived up in the pretty village of Lyndhurst, my little red Mitsubishi looking at little out of place alongside the line of Ferrari’s and Maserati’s parked outside Meridien Modena, the sports car dealership on the village’s High street, but it was at least matching the colour scheme. The necessary items we required were easily found in the local shops and so we set off towards the forest now armed with an OS map and stocked up with beer and venison sausages. We walked due south and peeled off into a small estate of 60s-built suburban houses and down a cul-de-sac which would humbly serve as our gateway into what was once the hunting ground of choice for William the Conqueror.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/newf/3-sunrise.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The trees rose up high on either side of us. Instantly the air was colder and the once-wide open blues skies of Hampshire where now reduced to the narrow void between the trees created by the broad path. There was a tangible sense that there is something special about the New Forest, perhaps it came from just how much life there is everywhere around you as you walk. The forest’s trees consist of ancient stands of burled and burly Oaks and Beeches standing in tall and elegant poses, and younger tracts of Silver Birch and Pine. And it is true that in the Autumn it is near-impossible to find a patch of ground that isn’t home to one of the thousands of fungi species the live here in symbiosis with the forest’s plants and trees. The forest floor is alive with colourful mushrooms, from the bright red and instantly recognisable Fly Agaric, to the myriad species of stout and chunky Boletus, and the much sought after golden-capped Chanterelle. Combine all of this with wild roaming ponies and you begin to build a picture of the New Forest in all it’s mythic splendour.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/newf/4-ponies.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We searched for a spot to camp, somewhere out of sight and quiet where we could pitch up without disturbing any wildlife. The ground here is very wet is covered with a thick carpet of sphagnum, and any deadwood we could find was rotten and completely useless as firewood. It was clear that a campfire was out of the question and so we cooked up a sausage stew on a the camp stove and drank our beers under the light of the moon. The night was full of noises, from the familiar and comforting hoots of Tawny Owls to the once haunting pained-barks of foxes, a sound all wild-campers become accustomed to, as well as some hoarse mammalian howls that I’ve never before heard or since.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We rose, well rested, to a perfect morning. The air was crisp and the sun’s golden light was spilling through the leaves of the trees. The forest had welcomed and rewarded us with its natural beauty and simplicity but it was now sadly time to leave and return to normality. We packed our kit away and took our path back to Lyndhurst, taking in once more the sheer loveliness of our host.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We stopped for espresso’s and bruschetta before hitting the road at an independent cafe, choosing to sit outside in the sunshine. We looked in that moment both cosmopolitan and disheveled, as if we were the latest incarnation of hipster, amping-up the lumberjack look to full-blown woodland tramp. Little did our passers-by know of our microadventure in the woods; our little slice of solitude far away from the complexities of modern life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the drive home I noticed that just a few of the leaves on the trees had started to show the first signs of oranging and loosening themselves from their branches. It seemed the seasons had hinged on our weekend. And just as one began to close another came into the fore, putting to rest the last hopes that the summer may just linger on in act of happy forgetfulness.             &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/newf/5-sunrise.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/newf/6-tarp.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/newf/7-beer.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/newf/8-mushroom.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 18 Feb 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>/features/24-newforest</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/features/24-newforest</guid>
        
        <category>microadventures</category>
        
        <category>mushrooms</category>
        
        <category>camping</category>
        
        
        <category>Features</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Photo Story: Edinburgh to Stornorway</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;My odyssey from the Scottish capital to the northern reaches of its Western Isles&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-plan&quot;&gt;1. The Plan&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/edstor/1-plan.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My chosen route for my cycle touring trip from Edinburgh to the the top of the Outer Hebrides islands back in the summer of 2015.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-means&quot;&gt;2. The Means&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/edstor/2-means.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is my rig for my ride from Edinburgh to the Outer Hebrides islands. If you’re not one for nerdy bike talk I recommend moving on now. You’ve been warned. This is my Kona Honkytonk, I know, I know, why didn’t you get the Kona Sutra, I hear you cycle-touring pros out there say. Well, I really would have preferred the Sutra but I couldn’t find it anywhere for less than £1200 and so finding this, a bike I had ridden before and liked a lot for £500 brand-new was really a no-brainer. It has a steel frame, heavy but strong and easily repairable compared to aluminium frames, and it looks great. I went for the tried-and-tested Ortlieb panniers and Brook’s saddle and just looked away from the laptop screen as I pressed the ‘use all your savings to buy this’ button. They are fantastic though.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I changed a few items for this trip to Scotland such as the tyres, I went for Schwalbe Marathons. Sure, they’re heavy but I can’t tell you the peace of mind afforded to you knowing that your chances of a puncture are reduced to almost nothing. In fact I didn’t get a single puncture during my trip and even gave away most of my repair kit to a fellow cycle tourer who had endless flats. I also removed the clip-in pedals and replaced them with cheapo flat pedals with the reasoning that I could wear more comfortable shoes while riding and that speed didn’t really matter anyway. Jury’s still out on whether this was really a good idea! I could go on a lot more about the rig but I appreciate we all have lives to live!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;leaving-home&quot;&gt;3. Leaving Home&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/edstor/3-leaving.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
Stevenage train station, packed and ready for the 5 hour train ride to Edinburgh.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;welcome-to-scotland&quot;&gt;4. Welcome to Scotland&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/edstor/4-welcome.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
The superb Forth railway bridge. I could at this point provide some highly dubious trivia, regarding how it’s always in the process of being painted, but I’ll spare you. The bridge I’m stood on in this picture, however, appears to be slowly falling apart. They have installed acoustic listening devices on the suspension cables to listen for the pings of breaking strands of steel, just to keep an eye on things. Reassuring.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;unexpected-adventures&quot;&gt;5. Unexpected Adventures&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/edstor/5-unexpected.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
What’s great about Scotland is that you can camp anywhere, more or less. On my first night I found a quiet and secluded meadow that looked perfect. The sky was clear and the stars were out so I opted for the bivvy bag - wild camping at it’s best if you ask me! However, what I had failed to realise was that this meadow was part of an active construction site. The sound of reversing sirens are a lot louder than the alarm on my phone and went off quite a bit earlier too! An exchange of thumb’s-up was had and I was soon on my way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;new-aquaintances&quot;&gt;6. New Aquaintances&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/edstor/6-new.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
I’m sure by this point you’re beginning to see that the main character of my trip was my trusty steed, Honky. What I don’t have, sadly, is many pictures of all the people I met on the way. Whilst heading through the Highlands towards Oban I met Colin from Wyoming who had been travelling across Europe and was on his final leg, cycling in Scotland. We were headed in the same direction for the next 50 miles or so, so we buddied up for the day. We stayed at a campsite that night and enjoyed a good night’s drinking down the local. The next day, a little sore-headed, we bid each other farewell and went on our separate ways.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;crossing-the-minch&quot;&gt;7. Crossing the Minch&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/edstor/7-crossing.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
From Oban it was a 5 hour ferry ride to Lochboisdale, which I spent with a fellow cycle tourer; an Aberdeen girl who was headed for Barra. The boat ride had it’s up’s and down’s, every 15 seconds or so, in a relentless swaying motion. I have never seen so much vomit. My companion had assured me she’d inherited an iron stomach from a long line of seafarer’s, the look on her face as she slowly made her way through the ferry canteens mac’n’cheese told a different story.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;night-rider&quot;&gt;8. Night-rider&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/edstor/8-night.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
I arrived on the Western Isles shortly after 11 to a pitch-black night. I put my lights on and cycled into the night. This was to be one of the best rides of my life, in complete darkness surrounded by the ethereal whirring of burrowing Puffins and the whistling wind. I cycled for a long way into the night until a car pulled up next to me. I was certain I had met my final bloody fate. The window of the car wound down and before appeared not an axe-wielding maniac looking for nocturnal cyclists but a friendly faced middle-aged woman. She asked me where I was headed, to which I replied ‘that way’, to which she said ‘there isn’t anything that way’. She recommended that I find a camp spot soon before heading into what was just squidgy swamps and pools for miles. She drove on and I set my bivvy up in the bus shelter a few yards up the road. This, unsurprisingly a poor place to camp, as I was the unwelcome visitor to what was already the home for every creepy crawly in the local vicinity. The morning light came as a relief. It also revealed my environment for the first time. A sparse, mostly treeless landscape with short rugged hills and endless tiny lochs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;a-sign-of-things-to-come&quot;&gt;9. A Sign of Things to Come&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/edstor/9-sign.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
Loved these signs, at a glance it looks like a dinosaur, Nessie even. Kept my eyes peeled for otters (and Nessie) but had no such luck.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;french-fried&quot;&gt;10. French-fried&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/edstor/10-french.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
These two french cyclists had spent the previous two days cycling together and went their separate ways not long after this picture was taken but not before sharing a wee dram of whisky and baileys too, plus a few tokes on our new friend’s jazz cigarette. Afterwards we all had a go at riding about recklessly on his recumbent bike, attempting to do skids in the middle of an A-road.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;crofting-on-berneray-island&quot;&gt;11. Crofting on Berneray Island&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/edstor/11-crofting.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
This is the Youth Hostel on the island of Berneray. On the way I passed by a village hall with a free wifi and by this point internet and phone signal had become a luxury, so I headed inside. I was met by an English couple. I politely asked if I could have the password, ‘Of course you can dear’ the lady said, ‘would you like to learn about the island’s history first?’, if only I had the courage to say no. I patiently leafed through binders of sepia photographs of stern faced school masters, fishermen, and priests, only to be told after a long history lesson that the internet was in fact down. Great! ‘But don’t worry,’ she said, ‘between you and me, the B-and-B down the road has a Wifi network with no password.’ I promised to keep my word and headed to the b-and-b, where sure enough I got some slow but usable free Wifi.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;psycho-killer&quot;&gt;12. Psycho Killer&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/edstor/12-psycho.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
Every hosteller’s worst nightmare: the axe-murderer, seen here moments before dealing the fatal blow. Thankfully this was not a real axe murderer but a fellow friendly traveller. That night there were a few of us staying in the old white-washed croft. Later in the evening a crusty old pirate-looking fellow turned up asking us if we wanted to buy some crab meat. Two young, and mute (up to this point) Italian sisters, looking a bit bewildered by their situation, piped up and took some of the crab from the man’s hamper. They had, however, misunderstood that the man would be expecting some recompense for his efforts and wasn’t just driving around doling out crab for nothing and so they shyly returned the crab. The man got very angry and huffed loudly the words ‘fucking timewasters’ before slamming the door, leaving his Jack Russell staring out through the window as his master trundled off in his old Rav4. It was scary, and we suspected he may be our axe-murderer. In the end his dog wandered off and we all woke up with the standard number of limbs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;harris-home-of-tweed&quot;&gt;13. Harris, Home of Tweed&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/edstor/13-harris.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
The next day I arrived on the Isle of Harris famous for it’s tweed. In fact, the Isle of Harris and the Isle of Lewis are indeed the same island, the only thing separating them being their geography, Lewis is largely flat and bleak, and Harris has some large, more Highland-like hills and mountains. You can see in the picture here a glimpse of the Hebrides’ famous white sands and aquamarine seas. If I could do this again I would allow myself more time to explore the beautiful beaches here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;rr&quot;&gt;14. R+R&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/edstor/14-rr.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
It took me a long time to get back on the road after staying at the youth hostel in Rhenigidale, partly because it served such luxuries as this wood-burning stove and a DAB radio, but mostly because I knew would have to cycle up and over a mountain I had to cycle over to get here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;facing-the-inevitable&quot;&gt;15. Facing the Inevitable&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/edstor/15-facing.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
Aforementioned mountain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;back-to-the-mainland&quot;&gt;16. Back to the Mainland&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/edstor/16-back.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
The next day took me to Stornoway where I spent the night in an overpriced hotel, ate pub food, drank beer, and watched TV. The journey across Lewis had been bleak with really not much to speak of other than the brief glimpse of a White-tailed Eagle. The next day I took the ferry to Ullapool, the crossing taking us past the pointed peaks of Skye and I offering sightings of dolphins as they leaped from the water beside the boat. I loaded my bike on to the bike bus in Ullapool which took me to Inverness where I was to catch the sleeper train back home the following day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;journeys-end&quot;&gt;17. Journey’s End.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/edstor/17-end.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
Dusk in Inverness on the final night of my trip. When I arrived at the station I was informed that there was no room for my bike on the train by an officious train guard standing in front of the mile-long Caledonian Sleeper train and that a courier would be driving it in a van to London. My whole experience on the sleeper was pretty dismal to be honest and I glad when it was over. Back in London I waited on a back street near Euston for a white van to turn up with my bike. A different man arrived from the one I’d handed my bike to in Scotland, and an hour late at that.  My annoyance was neutralised when I noticed he’d made his part of the journey through the night with his young child sleeping in the front of his van, I thanked him and cycled to Kings-Cross where I caught the train home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;album&quot;&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;
        &lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/edstor/album1.jpg&quot; /&gt;

    &lt;/figure&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;
        &lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/edstor/album2.jpg&quot; /&gt;

    &lt;/figure&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;
        &lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/edstor/album3.jpg&quot; /&gt;

    &lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 14 Feb 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>/features/cycling-scotland</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/features/cycling-scotland</guid>
        
        <category>cycling</category>
        
        <category>adventure</category>
        
        <category>photostories</category>
        
        
        <category>Features</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Jack Wolfskin Gossamer 1 Review</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Internal dimensions: Length 230cm, Height 70cm, Width 95cm&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Construction: PU coated 75D Polyester, Alloy poles and pegs&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Weight: 1550g&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pack size: 45cmx17cm&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;dl&gt;
  &lt;dt&gt;Pros&lt;/dt&gt;
  &lt;dd&gt;Great build quality&lt;/dd&gt;
  &lt;dd&gt;Striking design&lt;/dd&gt;
  &lt;dd&gt;Relatively cheap&lt;/dd&gt;
  &lt;dt&gt;Cons&lt;/dt&gt;
  &lt;dd&gt;Tough to pitch correctly&lt;/dd&gt;
  &lt;dd&gt;Damp problems&lt;/dd&gt;
  &lt;dd&gt;Limited storage&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/gossamer/cover.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;The Gossamer in all it&#39;s saggy glory.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I bought my Gossamer from OutdoorGear.co.uk for £75 last April, before the BoldlyGoes trip to Spain.  I initially chose it over the Wild Country Zephyros 1, due to it’s interesting design and £35 price difference. The two-pole tunnel design isn’t a popular tent design, but it looks great and pitching is a breeze, even in bad conditions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;build-quality&quot;&gt;Build Quality&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The build quality of the Gossamer is remarkably good, 10 months after purchase, and dozens of pitches later, all of the seams are still tight, the DAC poles are as good as new, and although I lost one peg, the others are all still straight despite quite a lot of abuse.  The one component which requires improvement is the ground sheet, which professes to have a 5,000mm hydrostatic head, but will let beads of moisture through by the morning.  The tent includes only 10 pegs while the design actually requires 12 including guy lines, but unless it’s very windy, these are optional.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/gossamer/pack.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;High quality materials and a small pack size make it attractive for backpackers.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;design&quot;&gt;Design&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The design of the Gossamer straddles the line between the low, compact, hooped bivvys and the roomier 1 man backpacking tents with room to sit up and porches to store your backpack.  This fusion results in a compromised experience, just entering the tent requires some thought, the door is at the head end rather than at the side, this requires you to stand up in the entrance, then filter yourself into the tent and your sleeping bag at the same time, feet first.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Gossamer has a large unsupported mid section, which ends up sagging however tight I pitch, this sag, seen in most hooped bivvys is not an issue with single walled gore-tex designs.  But coupled with the double walled design of the gossamer, this sag results in condensation soaking your clothes or sleeping bag after even the smallest movements during the night or morning.  This sag could be solved easily with two extra guy lines halfway up either side of the tent, but the curved design limits the options there without pulling the top of the tent flat.  Having pitched the tent in a number of ways, I can’t seem to adjust it to the point where there is a gap between the fly and the mesh inner.  This wouldn’t be a huge problem in a tent which was slightly larger, I’ve seen several larger double walled tents with no space between the fly and the inner, but if you roll over in your sleeping bag at night in those you won’t be touching the sides of the tent.  In a compact design like this one, it results in guarranteed dampness when you move around.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The lack of a porch or any storage space is an issue; there isn’t room for anything larger than a 35 litre backpack inside next to you, and only boots can be stored in between the two walls.  If you’re camping in colder weather or have a lot of gear with you, the only option is to stick the whole lot in a dry bag and leave it outside, not entirely secure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you are inside (and as long as you don’t move too much), the Gossamer is very cosy, the lack of space actually means it warms up very quickly.  There is a useful guy line running along the ceiling of the tent where you can hang lights, it also tensions the ceiling to stop a little bit of that lethal sag.  The low design lends itself to stability in high winds and the position of the side pegs does afford some control over the airflow into the tent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;alternatives&quot;&gt;Alternatives&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I’ve said, the Gossamer has slotted itself into a strange place in the market, where it finds itself competing with budget tents, more expensive entry level backpacking tents and most hooped bivvys.  My second choice when looking for a tent was the Wild Country Zephyros 1, this much roomier back packing tent features a porch, room to sit up and change and weighed slightly less, but it was £35 more expensive.  The Snugpak Stratosphere Hooped Bivi features a superior construction quality and materials, but had even less storage space and the same £35 price difference.  The Highlander Blackthorn 1 was the budget option at half the price of the Gossamer, has the same design as the now legendary Gelert Solo, but suffered from terrible build quality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;bg-scroll&quot; style=&quot;background-image: url(&#39;/media/img/gossamer/reverse.jpg&#39;)&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;final-thoughts&quot;&gt;Final Thoughts&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In conclusion, the Gossamer 1 would be a great first tent for anyone given its modest price tag, but it is let down by the lack of conviction in it’s design, or possibly it’s total conviction to not be like any other tent on the market. When I want to sit in my tent and watch the rain, I am forced to just get up like when I am bivvy bagging.  When I feel cosy and warm like in a bivvy bag, I get damp from the condensation like I am in a cramped tent.  It’s the best and worst of both worlds, but no one fault completely hampers the experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t regret the purchase and I can see it surviving at least two or three more seasons, it isn’t too heavy or bulky enough to put me off carrying it on longer hikes.  However, if it broke I would not buy it again, if I were buying a tent in the same price range again, I’d spend a little extra for the added comfort and gear security offered by the Wild Country Zephyros 1.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/gossamer/door.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;The Gossamer never finds it&#39;s stride, but it&#39;s still a well made starter tent.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;rating-24&quot;&gt;Rating: 2/4&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Entry level gear that we probably wouldn’t buy again if it broke.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 09 Feb 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>/reviews/gossamer-review</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/reviews/gossamer-review</guid>
        
        <category>reviews</category>
        
        <category>tents</category>
        
        <category>gear</category>
        
        
        <category>Reviews</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Our trip to the Picos de Europa</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Picos de europa
Lorem ipsum dolor sit amet, consectetur adipiscing elit. Donec non felis sit amet diam egestas eleifend in at felis. Aliquam quis velit a ante vulputate viverra eu et felis. Vestibulum luctus arcu id risus semper, in cursus lectus iaculis. Integer mattis sagittis diam. Cras eget convallis enim, in condimentum odio. Vestibulum non diam eget tellus condimentum sollicitudin. Quisque imperdiet tincidunt urna, sit amet convallis massa accumsan sed. Curabitur tristique suscipit convallis. Fusce efficitur quis erat ac ullamcorper. Nulla varius feugiat sapien, vitae laoreet ligula imperdiet ac. Donec sit amet nunc pretium, pharetra tortor ut, faucibus ipsum. Donec consequat pretium fringilla. Maecenas sed dui fringilla, porttitor nunc vitae, accumsan quam. Nullam erat odio, gravida sit amet hendrerit non, ultrices eu ante. Vestibulum ante ipsum primis in faucibus orci luctus et ultrices posuere cubilia Curae; Sed id dictum ante.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lorem ipsum dolor sit amet, consectetur adipiscing elit. Donec non felis sit amet diam egestas eleifend in at felis. Aliquam quis velit a ante vulputate viverra eu et felis. Vestibulum luctus arcu id risus semper, in cursus lectus iaculis. Integer mattis sagittis diam. Cras eget convallis enim, in condimentum odio. Vestibulum non diam eget tellus condimentum sollicitudin. Quisque imperdiet tincidunt urna, sit amet convallis massa accumsan sed. Curabitur tristique suscipit convallis. Fusce efficitur quis erat ac ullamcorper. Nulla varius feugiat sapien, vitae laoreet ligula imperdiet ac. Donec sit amet nunc pretium, pharetra tortor ut, faucibus ipsum. Donec consequat pretium fringilla. Maecenas sed dui fringilla, porttitor nunc vitae, accumsan quam. Nullam erat odio, gravida sit amet hendrerit non, ultrices eu ante. Vestibulum ante ipsum primis in faucibus orci luctus et ultrices posuere cubilia Curae; Sed id dictum ante.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lorem ipsum dolor sit amet, consectetur adipiscing elit. Donec non felis sit amet diam egestas eleifend in at felis. Aliquam quis velit a ante vulputate viverra eu et felis. Vestibulum luctus arcu id risus semper, in cursus lectus iaculis. Integer mattis sagittis diam. Cras eget convallis enim, in condimentum odio. Vestibulum non diam eget tellus condimentum sollicitudin. Quisque imperdiet tincidunt urna, sit amet convallis massa accumsan sed. Curabitur tristique suscipit convallis. Fusce efficitur quis erat ac ullamcorper. Nulla varius feugiat sapien, vitae laoreet ligula imperdiet ac. Donec sit amet nunc pretium, pharetra tortor ut, faucibus ipsum. Donec consequat pretium fringilla. Maecenas sed dui fringilla, porttitor nunc vitae, accumsan quam. Nullam erat odio, gravida sit amet hendrerit non, ultrices eu ante. Vestibulum ante ipsum primis in faucibus orci luctus et ultrices posuere cubilia Curae; Sed id dictum ante.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 13 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>/features/picos-de-europa</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/features/picos-de-europa</guid>
        
        <category>adventure</category>
        
        <category>hiking</category>
        
        <category>climbing</category>
        
        
        <category>Features</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>James&#39; Overnight Kit </title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;This is currently what will be found in my bag if I was out for just a night or two in the woods. Everything I need (not just to survive a night outdoors but enjoy it in great comfort too) can fit into this 35 litre rucksack. And in many ways, out of all the different configurations of gear I have, whether it’s for a multi-day trip by bike or on foot, or just a day out on the hills; this overnight pack is perhaps my most refined: pared down to the essentials but without compromising on comfort.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is no tent; just a hammock, bivvy, and tarp - and to be honest, if the weather is looking good the tarp will stay at home. I will take this opportunity to endorse relegating your tent from your overnight setup and switching to a hammock. It is lighter, much more comfortable, and there is no better sight to wake up to than the sun breaking through a thick canopy of green.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Below is a walkthrough of all my gear with a brief description of what is and how it found its way into my bag (and perhaps what it pushed out too).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/img/overnight_kit.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;My kit and packed bag.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;lowe-alpine-airzone-35-litre-rucksack&quot;&gt;Lowe Alpine Airzone 35 litre Rucksack&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;ENO Double Nest Hammock -  I bought this while I was in the States from a huge outdoor store called REI. It was a steal at just $30 or $40 (I can’t remember exactly now). Sadly, these seem hard to get in the UK without having to pay out a little more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;oex-34-length-self-inflating-sleeping-pad&quot;&gt;OEX 3/4 length self inflating sleeping pad&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is made by Go Outdoor’s exclusive brand OEX, as a cheaper alternative to a Thermarest I think it is very good indeed. You can read a full review here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;british-army-gore-tex-bivvy-bag&quot;&gt;British Army Gore-tex Bivvy bag&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Love this bivvy, sure it takes up more space in my bag than other bags but it is extremely breathable, tough, and big enough to stow your rucksack in the bottom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;vango-planet-50-sleeping-bag&quot;&gt;Vango Planet 50 sleeping bag&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cheap and cheerful. Packs really small and is more than good enough for a warm summers night.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;tarp&quot;&gt;Tarp&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;morakniv-knife&quot;&gt;Morakniv Knife&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you haven’t got one, get one. Amazing value for such a high quality knife.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;zebra-14cm-billy-can&quot;&gt;Zebra 14cm Billy Can&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Really nicely made billy can that quickly found a permanent spot in my bag despite being slightly cumbersome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;msr-pocket-rocket&quot;&gt;MSR pocket Rocket&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Small, powerful, and won’t leave too much of a dent in the wallet. Only complaint, when rigged up on top of a gas can with a pot of boiling water perched on top it does topple very easily.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;camelbak-podium-water-bottles&quot;&gt;Camelbak Podium Water Bottles&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I bought these for cycle touring and now they come everywhere with me. They have great locking valves that never leak in the bottom of your bag.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;moleskin-notepad-and-pencil&quot;&gt;Moleskin Notepad and Pencil&lt;/h4&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 05 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>/features/overnight-kit</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/features/overnight-kit</guid>
        
        <category>gear</category>
        
        <category>microadventures</category>
        
        
        <category>Features</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>24 hours: in Norfolk</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;It’s only 6 o’clock but it feels like the middle of the night. In truth, I really think even the middle of the night during summer would pale in comparison to the heavy veil of darkness laid upon us by that of the bleak days of November. It was perhaps against conventional wisdom to be camping that night but there we were anyway, sat on the Norfolk coast, not far from Wells-next-the-Sea, mesmerised by the lights of nearby fishing boats slowly panning our horizon and comforted by many layers of clothing and a box of fine Spanish wine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;bg-scroll&quot; style=&quot;background-image: url(&#39;/media/img/norfolk.jpg&#39;)&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’d arrived just in time to see the last of daylight and walked beneath vast formations of geese veeing over as they returned through pale blue skies to winter on our shores. Everyone else was walking home whilst we headed in the opposite direction, towards the dunes, adorned with large rucksacks and armed with thinly veiled excuses in case we where met with prying questions as to what it was we were up to. Of course, we only met smiles and hello’s and not so much as a glimpse of suspicion from anyone that we may be planning to camp (illegally) amongst the band of coniferous trees that defends the landed Holkham estate from the encroaching sea.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet, as is always the case in England, we skulked into the woods, hoping to not be seen and reserving a place in the backs of our minds for fears of being caught and lumped with convictions for trespassing. Whenever we wild camp we are meticulous when it comes to clearing any scrap of evidence that would betray our presence and are mindful that we are not welcome to loiter, but rather we should always arrive late and leave early and stay no more than one night. And still we gladly do these things so that we can spend some time in nature, uninterrupted by the pressures of modern life and fully immersed in our surroundings. During a winter camp this translates to being constantly surprised by just how early it is and being forced to live at winters pace, throwing our circadian rhythms back into long-lost kilter, and also to having the chance to be the sole inhabitants of a stretch of one of England’s most beautiful beaches for a night. Because for that night it all belonged to us: the crashing waves, the distant flickering lights of the wind farms, the murmuring masses of geese roosting in the salt marshes, and the heavy black sky pierced by myriad silver stars.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;bg-scroll&quot; style=&quot;background-image: url(&#39;/media/img/norfolk1.jpg&#39;)&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We returned from the beach, carefully retracing our way back in to the woods to our camp and went about chewing the fat (literally, in the case of my curry) beside the small fire we’d lit and the before too long went to bed, probably earlier than we’ve been in years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next morning we awoke to the pattering of rain on the canvasses above us, a quintessential sound of camping. Despite urges to stay hunkered down, cozy in our sleeping bags, we got up and quickly dismantled our shelters and went about forensically replacing logs, twigs, and leaf litter to mask any indication of our camp and headed back to civilisation and normality where we’ll stay until we find our next adventure.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 01 Nov 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>/features/24-norfolk</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/features/24-norfolk</guid>
        
        <category>microadventures</category>
        
        <category>beach</category>
        
        <category>camping</category>
        
        
        <category>Features</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
