<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>BoldlyGoes</title>
    <description></description>
    <link>http://boldlygoes.co.uk//</link>
    <atom:link href="http://boldlygoes.co.uk//feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Wed, 07 Oct 2015 16:00:04 +0100</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 07 Oct 2015 16:00:04 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v2.5.3</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Great Barford</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;boldly-going-where-quite-a-few-people-have-gone-before&quot;&gt;Boldly going where quite a few people have gone before&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whilst BoldlyGoes has big ambitions (Danube ahoy), the team is learning as we go. So obviously, we need as many practise trips and as much deep-thought (drunken) planning as possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;James, current BoldyGoes leader and wacky kayak modification engineer, scoped out a lovely spot for our first group excursion onto the water. Great Barford is a splendid little village located in Bedfordshire. Through it, runs the River Ouse which was James’ chosen location for our first day out on the water. The calm water surrounding a lovely arched road bridge, which spans the river Ouse coming into Great Barford, was the perfect location for our first splash and paddle. The river is navigable by barge – there is a lock and weir located 200m north of the bridge – so there was the occasional locked-eye stare with any passing river travellers, but for the most part, this length of water served our needs perfectly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;//boldlygoes.co.uk/assets/images/barford_bridge_water.jpg&quot; data-lightbox=&quot;barford-bridge&quot; data-title=&quot;Idyllic and in Bedfordshire - diamond in the rough&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;//boldlygoes.co.uk/assets/images/barford_bridge_water.jpg&quot; title=&quot;Idyllic and in Bedfordshire - diamond in the rough&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you were rating this waterway like a colour coded ski slope, where green is a nursery slope aimed towards beginners and black is an extremely challenging slope which should only be attempted by experts, then the part of the Ouse which runs through Barford Village would definitely be a sickly lime colour, which was fine by us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;James brought with him his inflatable kayak, a cheap and cheerful Sevylor Riviera 2 Person, which served as our mode of transport for the day. The kayak pack is built with backpack straps for easy transportation and is relatively easy to blow up and assemble, taking between 5-10 minutes in total. James was first out, going knee deep into the sloped entrance to the water before leaping into the kayak, paddle in hand. After showing us how it was done, Sam and myself both took the mighty Sevylor out for a spin. While it was fun out on the water and great to practise with (or learn how to use), we quickly identified the limitations of this inflatable vessel and why it is not best suited for a long expedition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;//boldlygoes.co.uk/assets/images/sevylor_top.jpg&quot; data-lightbox=&quot;sevylor-top&quot; data-title=&quot;Drone strike in-bound&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;//boldlygoes.co.uk/assets/images/sevylor_top.jpg&quot; title=&quot;Drone strike in-bound&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Sevylor is completely inflatable, i.e. there are no rigid sections. With your standard rigid canoe or kayak the hard base creates a full length rudder which is controlled when you make a stroke. On the Sevylor, the lack of any rigid base, or a dedicated rudder makes controlled steering pretty challenging. This ends up in a lot of effort being exerted on constantly maintaining direction rather than being able to charge along stroke after stroke. Sure, some of this will be down to technique, or lack of, but the non rigid base certainly has an impact, and would result in a lot of wasted energy on a long trip. This is compounded by two other things: the fact that, unfortunately it isn’t that comfy. The seating, which isn’t secured, needs constant readjustment; and also, we found that it started to gradually deflate, needing more air after about an hour. On a long trip, you will get a puncture, once that happens, sure, you can fix it up but from that point on, you could always get stuck with a deflated kayak in the middle of a river, with all your gear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, we very quickly came to conclusion that, whilst inflatables are practical to transport, in the long term they probably wouldn’t be that practical for transporting you. What’s our next step? Day out on the Ouse with rigid kayaks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Worth noting, James had some fun with a makeshift sail but I won’t spoil that for you in this post.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 01 Oct 2015 19:41:22 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://boldlygoes.co.uk//planning/2015/10/01/great-barford.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://boldlygoes.co.uk//planning/2015/10/01/great-barford.html</guid>
        
        <category>sevylor</category>
        
        <category>kayaking</category>
        
        <category>barford</category>
        
        <category>planning</category>
        
        <category>testing</category>
        
        
        <category>planning</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Exploring The Danube: A Plan Is Born</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Pest and Buda, once two separate cities, were connected permanently for the first time in 1849 by
the Chain Bridge, an impressive suspension
bridge spanning the 400 metre-wide River
Danube. Before its construction, crossing
between the two cities was a much more
arduous task, calling for the use of ferries
and improvised wooden bridges, and was
at all times entirely under the will of the
weather. In fact, the harsh Hungarian
winters could leave hopeful river-crossers
stranded for days or even weeks at a time.
That was until the river left Count István
Széchenyi, an ample-eyebrowed Hungarian
statesman, stuck and unable to cross the
river in order to attend his father’s funeral.
The unfortunate event inspired him to take action and commission the building of bridge large
enough to withstand anything the weather and the river’s power could throw at it. An English
engineer by the name of William Tierney Clark was handed the job of realising the Count’s vision.
He based the Chain Bridge on a small bridge he had built in Buckinghamshire crossing the
Thames in the village of Marlow. It was this bridge that first connected the two cities and served as
a catalyst in establishing the metropolis of Budapest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/f/fd/Sz%C3%A9chenyi_Chain_Bridge_in_Budapest_at_night.jpg&quot; data-lightbox=&quot;chainbridge-large&quot; data-title=&quot;The Chain Bridge spanning the Danube.&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/f/fd/Sz%C3%A9chenyi_Chain_Bridge_in_Budapest_at_night.jpg&quot; title=&quot;The Chain Bridge in Budapest.&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we stood upon the Bridge under the beating sun and the
watchful eyes of two large limestone lions reminiscent of those in
Trafalgar square, we listened to our tour guide recite this story of
how the bridge had come to be. Around stood many like us, a
haggard group of Englishmen wearied by the previous night’s
consumption of alcohol and loud Euro-House. We were in beautiful
Budapest, nine-strong, celebrating the marriage of our friend
Alasdair. Whilst listening to our guide I couldn’t help but notice the
Danube beneath us. Wide and shimmering blue. All too inviting. I
pictured myself paddling down it on some future adventure and
casually suggested the idea to Raj and Harvey to which they casually concurred.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/assets/images/chain-bridge-lion.jpg&quot; data-lightbox=&quot;lion-large&quot; data-title=&quot;One of four imposing Limestone Lions.&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/chain-bridge-lion.jpg&quot; title=&quot;One of four imposing limestone lions guarding the bridge.&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fast forward three weeks and the same group of Englishmen are well-oiled once again but this
time in an ornately decorated Hertfordshire village hall for Alasdair and Gabrielle’s wedding. The
passing thought of taking a trip down Europe’s second longest river had by now been stewing in 
my mind for some time. I had been secretly poring over maps of Europe, measuring the distances
between the River’s most notable sights and cities, reading up on canoes and packrafts. Silently
scheming. I had by this point already planned in my mind a journey between the once sprawling
Austro-Hungarian empire’s two capital cities: Vienna and Budapest. A journey of 250km passing
through Bratislava and Esztergom situated on the shoreline of the river’s main channel as well as a
maze of slowly shifting tributaries and offshoots in the vast floodplains of Dunajské luhy. I broached
the subject once more, this time a little less casually: “We should canoe down the Danube next
year, it’d be fun!”. Admittedly a little drunk we had perhaps unwisely begun our journey. Oh boy, we
have a lot to do!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 17 Sep 2015 16:19:22 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://boldlygoes.co.uk//planning/2015/09/17/exploring-the-danube:-a-plan-is-born.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://boldlygoes.co.uk//planning/2015/09/17/exploring-the-danube:-a-plan-is-born.html</guid>
        
        <category>budapest</category>
        
        <category>planning</category>
        
        <category>danube</category>
        
        <category>well-oiled</category>
        
        
        <category>planning</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
